<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prince Henry his second anniversary· By Daniel Price Doctor in Divinity, of his Highnesse chaplaines</title>
            <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10055</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20300</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115207</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850426</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850426</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15628</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10055)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15628)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 970:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prince Henry his second anniversary· By Daniel Price Doctor in Divinity, of his Highnesse chaplaines</title>
                  <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes and are to be sold by Iohn Barnes over against St Pulchers Church [, London],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Prince Henries second anniversarie.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry Frederick, --  Prince of Wales, 1594-1612.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15628:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15628:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PRINCE HENRY HIS SECOND ANNIVERSARY.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ECCLESIASTICVS 50.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>VVho was as a morning ſtar in the midſt of a clowd.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> DANIEL PRICE Doctor in Divinity, one of his Highneſſe Chaplaines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Ioſeph Barnes and are to be ſold by <hi>Iohn Barnes</hi> over againſt S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pulchers <hi>Church.</hi> 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15628:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15628:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST ILLVSTRIOVS PRINCE PRINCE CHARLES <hi>Duke of</hi> CORNEWALL <hi>the happyneſſe of the preſent, &amp; hope of poſterity.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST <hi>Gratious</hi> PRINCE, my <hi>vowed Annuall</hi> ſervice to the <hi>memory</hi> of your bleſſed <hi>Brother</hi> craveth your ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; for, vnder the ſhadow of your <hi>Princely Cedar,</hi> I hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſire to ſpende my daies. Not only the <hi>praiſe</hi> of the <hi>dead,</hi> but alſo the <hi>profit of the living</hi> be my inducements to this worke; both which I hope, wilbe <hi>acceptable arguments</hi> to your <hi>Highneſſe.</hi> I am encouraged the rather <hi>herevnto,</hi> becauſe I ſee your <hi>Princely ſpirit</hi> dare looke <hi>death</hi> in the face, and can be content to hear, that as your renowmed bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's <hi>fortunes,</hi> ſo his <hi>fate</hi> alſo ſhall one day be yours. Many, and happy be your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> daies, that you may ſo long <hi>continue</hi> in the <hi>world,</hi> as the <hi>world</hi> ſhall <hi>continue;</hi> that <hi>goodneſse</hi> may guide, and <hi>Religion</hi> may guard you, both which will aſſure more <hi>ſafety</hi> to your <hi>precious
<pb facs="tcp:15628:3"/>ſoule,</hi> then the <hi>Prevention</hi> of the <hi>world,</hi> and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption</hi> of the <hi>Court</hi> can afford you: for theſe will ſanctifie the <hi>Circumſpection</hi> of the wiſe in helping you, and terrifie the <hi>Circumvention</hi> of the wicked from hurting you. So ſhall your Highnes remember your <hi>Creator</hi> in the daies of your youth, and walke in the pathes of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> before God, till you come to the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>Henoch</hi> to walk with God. In the mean time the great <hi>Palmoni</hi> the numbrer of times make your daies as happy as the daies of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noch,</hi> whoſe <hi>yeares</hi> were as many as the yearly <hi>daies</hi> of the <hi>ſunne:</hi> that in your <hi>felicity,</hi> you may ride on <hi>proſperouſly</hi> becauſe of <hi>truth,</hi> of <hi>meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and <hi>righteouſnes;</hi> and having ended your courſe in <hi>Grace</hi> you may begin never to end in <hi>glory.</hi> Which is the dayly praier of your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> moſt obſervant ſervant</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>DANIEL PRICE.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ex. Coll.</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Novemb. 6. the fatall day of Prince</hi> HENRIES <hi>deceaſe.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15628:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>PRINCE HENRIES SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COND ANNIVERSARIE.</head>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Iſpriſsion</hi> may aſſaile, and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi> ſeeke to <hi>ſilence,</hi> the <hi>memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials</hi> of thoſe gratious inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Gods glory, <hi>who</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing delivered out of the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the <hi>fleſh,</hi> be in ioy &amp; <hi>fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie,</hi> but religious <hi>Pietie</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God; and obſequious <hi>dutie</hi> towards man, doe both warne and warrant, our gratefull and faithfull remembrances of thoſe <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, of whom the world was not worthy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.28. Rev. 14.13.</note> who now reſt in the Lord, and are free from their <hi>Labours,</hi> which may ſeeme to be the motiue of <hi>Salomons</hi> ſpeech,<note place="margin">Eccl. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Eccl. 4.2. <hi>I praiſed the dead, which are already dead, more then the living which are yet aliue,</hi> and of the Reverend <hi>Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe</hi> of <hi>ancient</hi> times, which did adorne the <hi>names</hi> of the <hi>good,</hi> the <hi>wiſe,</hi> the <hi>iuſt,</hi> the <hi>valiant,</hi> and not only ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured their <hi>Perſons</hi> in their <hi>liues,</hi> but bemoaned the worlds loſſe by their <hi>deaths,</hi> and by their <hi>praiſes,</hi> held out the <hi>light</hi> of their vertuous <hi>Lampe,</hi> to lead others into thoſe <hi>wayes,</hi> which theſe <hi>worthies</hi> had walked in, with <hi>comfort,</hi> &amp; in which, they had finiſhed their race
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15628:4"/>with <hi>Conqueſt. Rude</hi> and <hi>polite, Divine,</hi> and <hi>Prophane</hi> hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory doth <hi>countenance</hi> the continuance of ſuch <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes,</hi> and therefore though <hi>Snakes</hi> may bite, &amp; <hi>dogs</hi> may barke, and nothing within the <hi>Circumference</hi> of <hi>heaven</hi> can be, without the <hi>compaſſe</hi> of <hi>cenſure, duty</hi> only being my <hi>Apologie,</hi> with a <hi>patient content and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of gaineſayers,</hi> I proceed in my profeſſed, <hi>ſervice,</hi> to the <hi>Annuall</hi> remembrance of my bleſſed <hi>Maſter Prince HENRY,</hi> S. Auſtins rule being my reaſon, <hi>Nec laudantem movet adulatio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſtin</note> 
               <hi>nec laudatum tentat elatio,</hi> when neither he that praiſeth, is moved with <hi>flattery,</hi> nor he that is <hi>praiſed,</hi> can be tempted with <hi>vaine-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> when neither <hi>affection</hi> enticeth, nor <hi>opinion</hi> entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleth, it may be both <hi>lawfull</hi> and <hi>vſefull</hi> that the <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,</hi> may be had in <hi>everlaſtinſt remembrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 It being now therefore the <hi>entrance</hi> of the <hi>third</hi> yeare,<note n="*" place="margin">The fatall <hi>6.</hi> of Novemb.</note> ſince it pleaſed the Lord to deliuer the <hi>Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly firſt borne</hi> out of the <hi>miſery</hi> of this <hi>ſinfull world,</hi> and that the Winter <hi>Sables</hi> of <hi>November</hi> doe now repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent our former <hi>ſorrowes,</hi> it will be not <hi>vnſeaſonable</hi> to remember the <hi>holy</hi> paſſage of <hi>that heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſoule,</hi> which was freed from <hi>Adams</hi> body, to bee tranſlated to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> boſome, and his <hi>ſpirit</hi> to returne to God that gaue it. So in our <hi>obſervance</hi> running with <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> to the Sepulchre now, our eies haue loſt him, &amp; our feet cannot followe him, our <hi>ſpirituall ambition</hi> may lead our <hi>contemplation</hi> where he is, and <hi>ſeaſon</hi> our ſoules with ioy, to knowe what he is. For, <hi>what other is he</hi> (if we dare looke vpon the ſacred blaze of <hi>aeternitie</hi>) then a <hi>Celestiall</hi> ſpirit, and glorious <hi>Saint,</hi> a Piller in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15628:4"/>Temple of God, one of thoſe fed with that <hi>Manna,</hi> cloathed with the <hi>white robe,</hi> called by the <hi>new name,</hi> carying the triumphant <hi>Palme</hi> in his hand, following the <hi>Lambe,</hi> whether ſoever hee goeth. An immortall glorious <hi>Creature, Partaker</hi> with the beſt, &amp; moſt bleſt of <hi>Saints,</hi> more beauteous then the <hi>ſtarres,</hi> &amp; equall to <hi>Angels,</hi> A Divine ſeparated ſoule, refined and <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed,</hi> by beholding Gods vnvtterable <hi>maieſtie,</hi> in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying whereof the <hi>Angels</hi> are <hi>inſatiable,</hi> and inceſſant in the <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>Lawd</hi> thereof. A fixed <hi>ſtar,</hi> whoſe <hi>luſtre</hi> is as full of <hi>beautie</hi> as <hi>glory.</hi> A ſubſtance more <hi>pure</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>heavens,</hi> more <hi>orient</hi> then the riſing of the <hi>Sunne. How excellent is HEE in thy Tabernacles, O Lord of hoſts,</hi> where being <hi>delighted</hi> with all maner of <hi>ſatietie: ſatiety</hi> breeds no maner of diſlike, where now <hi>HEE</hi> hath the <hi>endowments</hi> of an heavenly <hi>inhabitant,</hi> and knows the difference betweene the <hi>conditions</hi> of a <hi>momentary,</hi> &amp; <hi>eternall life,</hi> and though the <hi>Immortalitie</hi> of his <hi>body</hi> haue not yet enioyed the <hi>rights</hi> of that world, eternall <hi>bliſſe,</hi> of the <hi>ſoule,</hi> ſhal one day entertaine the <hi>body</hi> with eternall <hi>beautie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 It was <hi>Davids</hi> precept to <hi>Solomon</hi> his ſonne,<note place="margin">1. Chr. 28.9.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon</hi> my ſonne knowe thou the God of thy <hi>father,</hi> and ſerue him with a perfit heart, and willing minde, and it was <hi>Ioſiahs</hi> practiſe, <hi>that in the eight yeare of his raigne, when he was yet a child,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chr. 24.3.</note> 
               <hi>he began to ſeeke after the God of David his father,</hi> where, as <hi>Alexander</hi> was inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Achilles</hi> example, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> by <hi>Alexander:</hi> So <hi>David</hi> moveth <hi>Solomon,</hi> and <hi>Ioſias</hi> is enflamed by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> religious profeſſion. Theſe Renowned <hi>worthies</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15628:5"/>began early,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.5.</note> and <hi>gloriouſly</hi> came forth as a <hi>bridegroome</hi> out of the <hi>Chamber,</hi> and reioyced as <hi>Giants,</hi> to runne their <hi>courſe,</hi> Prince <hi>HENRY</hi> was the true repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe. In him God had ſet a <hi>Tabernacle</hi> for the <hi>ſunne, Wiſdome, Religion, Vallor,</hi> did ſhine in his <hi>bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming,</hi> his <hi>firſt fruits</hi> ſhewed that the Lord had ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon <hi>him</hi> the gratious <hi>dewe of his inheritance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. Mat. 6.33.</note> 
               <hi>he did firſt ſeeke the kingdome of God, and the righteouſnes there of, &amp; referred the adminiſtration of other things to the</hi> hand of Providence, <hi>Iudgement</hi> did maſter <hi>opinion,</hi> and by <hi>earely accuſtoming</hi> his <hi>taſte</hi> to the <hi>truth</hi> of <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall pleaſure,</hi> hee contemned the <hi>falſe</hi> and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the <hi>filthy</hi> pleaſures of the worlde, <hi>luſt</hi> or <hi>pride</hi> could not <hi>faſten</hi> vpon him a deſire to <hi>ſpend,</hi> nor <hi>avarice</hi> a thirſt to <hi>ſpare, feare or favour</hi> could not cauſe him to preferre <hi>ſhaddowes,</hi> or <hi>neglect</hi> draw him from <hi>rewarding</hi> the meaneſt <hi>deſervers, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition</hi> drew him not to haſty <hi>adventures,</hi> nor <hi>daunger</hi> ever put him to <hi>distruſt,</hi> the <hi>ſunne beames</hi> of his <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> were moſt <hi>radian,</hi> yet his thoughts <hi>calme,</hi> and a heavenly <hi>peace</hi> in all his <hi>paſſions,</hi> his bleſſed <hi>minde</hi> was never racked with <hi>deſire</hi> or <hi>feare,</hi> nor ever <hi>troubled</hi> with the ſad <hi>burthens</hi> and conſuming CANKERS of this life, never afflicted with the <hi>ſurbate</hi> of cares or <hi>ſurfet</hi> of riots, <hi>froathy</hi> praiſe he avoided as <hi>infectious goodneſſe</hi> was his aime, which being the <hi>cauſe,</hi> led him on in the <hi>courſe</hi> of all thoſe moſt <hi>honourable</hi> actions, he entended, in all which, he was free from the <hi>taint,</hi> much more from the <hi>ſtaine</hi> or <hi>ſting</hi> of ill: <hi>Sophocles</hi> his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Sophoc. Xenoph.</note> or <hi>Xenophon</hi> in his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nay with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15628:5"/>al reverence to holy records, <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> or <hi>Ioſias</hi> ſo ſoone, did not ſo <hi>much,</hi> the later and the <hi>better</hi> of theſe began but in <hi>the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> yeare of his age, in the 8 yeare of his raigne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chron. 1.3.</note> but bleſſed PRINCE HENRY as if he had beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated from the <hi>wombe,</hi> in the <hi>morning watch</hi> of his life, was a <hi>morning starre</hi> in his luſtre, and conſidered that the Feare of God which the preacher made to bee the ende of all things in the end of his <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> the ſame is the <hi>beginning of wiſdome</hi> in the beginning of his <hi>Proverbs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.13.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 1.7.</note> Neither <hi>differring</hi> nor <hi>diſsembling</hi> had place in him, or power over him, no <hi>excuſes</hi> no <hi>refulals</hi> ſtaid him, he <hi>Remembred</hi> his <hi>Creator in the daies of his youth,</hi> he thought it good for him to beare the Lordes yoake in <hi>his youth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam 3.27.</note> he ſtudied wherewith a <hi>young</hi> man might cleanſe his waies, louely <hi>Iſaac,</hi> loving <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> Princely <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> true harted <hi>David,</hi> beloved <hi>Daniel,</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Samuel,</hi> faithful <hi>Timothy</hi> were his <hi>patternes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.9.</note> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrat his <hi>firſt</hi> &amp; beſt endeavours to <hi>God,</hi> Not only his <hi>Martiall</hi> &amp; <hi>Scholastical</hi> exerciſes did honour him with that title which <hi>Livy</hi> gaue to <hi>M. Cato, Si arma ſumpſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet in armis natu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crederes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">T. Livius Dec. <hi>4.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſi ſe ad ſtudia convertiſſet inter liter as educatum,</hi> but his <hi>dayly holy converſing with God in the path of goodneſſe,</hi> his ſpirituall <hi>progreſse</hi> in grace and favour teſtified that from his <hi>youth vp,</hi> his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation was <hi>in heaven,</hi> this was the <hi>grace</hi> of his <hi>childe hood,</hi> and <hi>garland</hi> of his <hi>youth,</hi> this <hi>bleſſed</hi> his <hi>life,</hi> &amp; <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted</hi> him at <hi>death,</hi> and ſhall <hi>commende</hi> him to all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Learne</hi> hence yee <hi>young Gallants,</hi> that put farre from you the day of the Lord, yee that neither in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15628:6"/>
               <hi>morning</hi> nor <hi>meridian</hi> of your liues, <hi>Prepare your ſelues</hi> to meete <hi>the Lord,</hi> or care that when he commeth he may finde you <hi>watching</hi> and <hi>working.</hi> To <hi>die well,</hi> is a long <hi>art</hi> of a ſhort life, and a <hi>ſpeedy</hi> beginning is the ſhorteſt <hi>method</hi> to this <hi>longeſt</hi> art, <hi>Salomon</hi> telleth of a time,<note place="margin">Eccl. 3.2. 2. Cor. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>Eccleſs. 3.2. Tempus mortis,</hi> But as if that were too <hi>generall, Paul</hi> confineth that time to <hi>a day.</hi> 2. Cor. 6.2. <hi>dies ſalutis,</hi> and Chriſt limiteth the time of that day to an howre,<note place="margin">Mat 25.13.</note> Mat. 25.13. <hi>Hora acceptationis,</hi> In the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation Babylon</hi> is lamented that in <hi>one</hi> howre <hi>her iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is come,</hi> Rev. 18.10. that in <hi>one</hi> howre ſo <hi>great ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches came to naught,</hi> verſ. 17. and that <hi>in one howre</hi> ſhee was made <hi>de ſolate,</hi> verſ. 19. But <hi>times</hi> &amp; <hi>daies</hi> &amp; <hi>howres</hi> are <hi>ſcantled</hi> yet ſhorter,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.52.</note> by the Apoſtle, <hi>Iudgement ſhall be</hi> in a moment, in the <hi>twinckling of an eie,</hi> in the laſt <hi>trumpe,</hi> that as God gaue his <hi>law</hi> with the ſound of a <hi>trumpet,</hi> Exod. 19.16. So hee ſhall call for <hi>account of</hi> it with the ſound of the <hi>Trumphet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ex 19.16. 1. Cor. 15. <hi>Hieron.</hi>
               </note> 1. Cor. 15.52. How ſhrill ſhould this <hi>trumpe</hi> be ſtill in our eares as <hi>S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> witneſſed of his <hi>owne,</hi> ever ſounding and eccho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, <hi>that the ſureſt way to a good life is to beginne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times,</hi> conſidering that though Gods <hi>mercies</hi> often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times affords vs, <hi>many yeares</hi> to <hi>repent,</hi> yet his <hi>Iuſtice</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth not an <hi>howre to ſinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg.</note> 
               <hi>Peccanti Craſtinum non promiſit</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory,</hi> hee promiſeth not to <hi>morrow</hi> to the <hi>offendour,</hi> who is alwaies ready to receiue the <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent:</hi> How ſhould this <hi>conſideration</hi> draw vs on, <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hit enim non cogit Deus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſtin.</note> &amp; lead vs along by the waters <hi>of comfort,</hi> and <hi>admoniſh vs</hi> all if <hi>hitherto</hi> we haue <hi>neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected,</hi> to faſten vpon the <hi>first opportunity</hi> of ſeaſoning
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15628:6"/>
               <hi>our ſouls</hi> with that bleſſed ſpirit of <hi>Janctification,</hi> while they be fit for <hi>impreſsion,</hi> and that by a <hi>gracious medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> we conſider the race we are to <hi>run,</hi> and the many encombrances which <hi>alwaies</hi> croſſe vs, That, <hi>delay</hi> aug<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>menteth difficulties, and more do periſh by this <hi>Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> then by al the <hi>toiles</hi> &amp; <hi>guiles</hi> of Sathan, the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger we perſiſt in <hi>ſin,</hi> the more God <hi>plucketh</hi> his <hi>grace</hi> and aſſiſtance from vs, our good <hi>inclinations</hi> are the <hi>weaker,</hi> the <hi>vnder ſtanding</hi> more <hi>darkned,</hi> the <hi>will</hi> more <hi>perverted,</hi> the <hi>appetite</hi> more <hi>diſordered,</hi> the <hi>paſsions</hi> are more <hi>strengthned,</hi> that at <hi>length</hi> the <hi>stupid</hi> and <hi>benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> ſoule, may looſe the <hi>ſpirituall</hi> light of <hi>grace,</hi> &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall <hi>light</hi> of <hi>reaſon,</hi> and retaine only the <hi>ſenſuall twy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light</hi> of affections, common with <hi>bruit beaſts,</hi> &amp; ſo the the youth being il ſpent, <hi>Sathan</hi> wil plead poſſeſſion in age, &amp; therefore the <hi>dawning, ſpringing, morning,</hi> time of life muſt bee conſecrated to <hi>God,</hi> it was not only the piety of <hi>Iob</hi> to riſe vp earely in the morning of everie day to facrifice and ſanctifie his ſonne. Iob. 1.5.<note place="margin">Iob. 1.5.</note> But his <hi>owne practiſe</hi> in his owne young yeares in the <hi>morning</hi> of his <hi>life,</hi> in the <hi>daies</hi> of his <hi>youth,</hi> the ſecret of God was vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Tabernacle. Iob. 29.29.4. For this is the time as <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> deſcribeth it,<note place="margin">Iob. 29.4. <hi>Ambroſ.</hi>
               </note> wherein the eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>fier</hi> predominateth in the <hi>ſonnes</hi> of men, <hi>calore corporis feruente, eſtu ſanguinis vapor antis igneſcente, viribus invallida, conſilijs infirma, vitio calens, illecebroſa delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is, est Adoleſcentia,</hi> This is the <hi>ſpring</hi> of life, and how eaſily may <hi>a ſpring-tide</hi> drowne all the <hi>ſummer hopes</hi> of youth, the time <hi>of ſtrength</hi> and <hi>beauty</hi> both eaſily infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by <hi>heate</hi> of <hi>vanity,</hi> the time of <hi>growth</hi> &amp; <hi>activity,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15628:7"/>both ſoone nipped with the <hi>frost of mortality,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> now <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus acutior, auditus promptior, inceſſus rectior, vultus iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundior,</hi> now the ſunne of the <hi>vnderstanding</hi> doth moſt <hi>appeare,</hi> and the <hi>starres</hi> of the <hi>ſenſes</hi> moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly <hi>ſhine,</hi> then the 4. humors <hi>reſembling</hi> the 4. Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the <hi>liver</hi> as the <hi>ſea,</hi> the <hi>veines</hi> as the <hi>rivers,</hi> are in their moſt <hi>pure,</hi> moſt actiue <hi>operation,</hi> the <hi>heart</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable as the <hi>earth,</hi> is moſt fruitfull, and the <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance</hi> ſo amiable is, as the <hi>heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> beautiful, <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> then appearing is like <hi>Adam</hi> in his <hi>innocencie,</hi> it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the <hi>poſseſſor</hi> to be <hi>noted</hi> and called <hi>the childe of God</hi> this character is <hi>bonae ſpei nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cia, bonae indolis index, vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga diſciplinae, gloria co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcientiae cuſtos famae laus naturae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignae gratiae virtutum primitiae,</hi> as <hi>S. Bernard</hi> reverently collecteth the attributes. Alas? how is that <hi>ſparke</hi> of vnderſtanding, the ſmall <hi>portion</hi> of the <hi>vulgar</hi> dimmed with the miſt of <hi>preiudice,</hi> &amp; obſcured with the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt of <hi>Paſſion,</hi> that the naturall <hi>youngling,</hi> wil not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the things that are of <hi>God,</hi> contenting himſelfe with <hi>Salomons</hi> young man, to reioice in <hi>his youth,</hi> and let his heart <hi>cheere</hi> him, to walke in the waies of his <hi>heart</hi> and in the ſight of his <hi>owne</hi> eies,<note place="margin">Eccl. 11.9.</note> but not conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that for all theſe <hi>things</hi> God will bring him to <hi>iudgement,</hi> growing hereby to that <hi>Epidemicall</hi> caſe that <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> deſcribeth in ſuch a one,<note place="margin">Chryſ Hom. <hi>1.</hi> ad Pop.</note> 
               <hi>Difficilis fallibilis vehementioribus aegens fraenis Adoleſcens.</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful <hi>thornes</hi> then choaking the good ſeedes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and grace, cuſtomable evil <hi>actions</hi> being his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trollers of iudgement, <hi>ſeducers</hi> of will, <hi>betrayers</hi> of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, <hi>flatterers</hi> of vice, <hi>vnderminers</hi> of courage, <hi>ſlaues</hi> to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15628:7"/>weakeneſſe, <hi>infection</hi> of youth <hi>madneſſe</hi> of age, <hi>curſe</hi> of life and <hi>reproach</hi> of death. Is it not a <hi>witcheraft</hi> that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhould be ſo chained with <hi>inchantment,</hi> of a <hi>mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> eſtate, as ſcarce to thinke vpon the <hi>Condition,</hi> which never ſhall haue end, to <hi>ſatisfie</hi> the <hi>fleſh,</hi> a <hi>neſt</hi> of <hi>wormes</hi> and to neglect the ſoule a <hi>Companion</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> to <hi>deſire</hi> rather to <hi>fill vp met am naturae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beaux.</note> 
               <hi>Natures</hi> aimes of long life, then <hi>menſuram gratiae,</hi> Graces full meaſure of a <hi>good life,</hi> or <hi>Coronam gloriae</hi> to attaine <hi>Glories Crowne</hi> of eternall life; crooked <hi>waies,</hi> baſe <hi>wealth,</hi> falſe <hi>pleaſures,</hi> vaine <hi>hopes,</hi> lying <hi>promiſes,</hi> ſweete <hi>poyſon,</hi> and ſenſeleſſe <hi>ſenſuall ſatisfaction</hi> inticing their <hi>ſoules,</hi> to <hi>ioy</hi> in thoſe <hi>things,</hi> whereof <hi>they will be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſeeing the end of thoſe things is death. Adams</hi> apple, <hi>Eſaus</hi> broth, <hi>Iudas</hi> ſop, <hi>Babylons cup,</hi> are more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, with theſe <hi>ſonnes</hi> of diſobedience, then <hi>Henoks whirlewinde, Eliahs</hi> Chariot, <hi>Pauls</hi> aſſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or <hi>Iohns</hi> Revelation, and hereby many ſweetly <hi>tempered</hi> diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions. And worthy <hi>ſpirits</hi> are ſwallowed <hi>vp,</hi> &amp; led a way <hi>Captiue</hi> like the <hi>Gallant</hi> in the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> who went to the houſe of the <hi>Harlot,</hi> the way to hel going down to the <hi>chambers</hi> of death,<note place="margin">Prov 7.7.</note> in the <hi>prime</hi> and <hi>ſpring,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the <hi>fall</hi> of their <hi>leafe,</hi> continuing their <hi>life,</hi> in a wintry ſtormy <hi>Tempeſtuous</hi> courſe, the ſurges <hi>of lust</hi> beating the ſhip, till the <hi>ſailes</hi> of pride be torne with the <hi>windes</hi> of violent <hi>paſſions,</hi> puniſhing <hi>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues</hi> with that horrid curſe, <hi>Peccatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poena peccati,</hi> the guilt of one ſinne becommeth the puniſhment of another.</p>
            <p n="5">5 I cal to <hi>witneſſe</hi> againſt ſuch this <hi>Princely</hi> Saint, who having obtained a gracious <hi>report</hi> and received
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15628:8"/>the promiſe is now a <hi>triumphant Chiefetaine</hi> in the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Saints: whoſe <hi>Scutchion</hi> bare this<note n="*" place="margin">In the Lotte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Armory, and Funerall.</note> 
               <hi>Motto, Et nos fas extera quaerere regna,</hi> as if he had come into the world but to learne to die, and as <hi>Iſrael</hi> came through the wilderneſſe of <hi>Sin,</hi> to paſſe through it towardes the land of <hi>Caanan,</hi> he began to ſeeke as the text ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of <hi>Ioſias,</hi> 2. Chr. 34.3. the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the original im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting not only to <hi>ſeek</hi> &amp; to inquire with al dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as <hi>Avenarius</hi> rendreth it.<note place="margin">Aven.</note> But to <hi>conſult,</hi> to <hi>deliberate,</hi> to <hi>ſearch</hi> with all care, for any thing that pertained to the worſhip of God. Not ſo to ſeeke as <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion trained his <hi>thoughts</hi> from <hi>Macedon</hi> to <hi>Greece,</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Greece</hi> to <hi>Italy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut in vita Pyrrhi.</note> from <hi>Italy</hi> to <hi>Sicily,</hi> from thence to <hi>Africke,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Carthage,</hi> it was no <hi>earthly,</hi> no <hi>world<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly</hi> adventure, his <hi>chiefe</hi> ayme was at; though ſo farre as the <hi>Royall</hi> rights of his <hi>Puiſſant Ancestors,</hi> and the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to his <hi>Soveraigne</hi> Father, in a iuſt war might haue giuen <hi>cauſe,</hi> our vndaunted <hi>Alexander,</hi> needed no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, for hee was ſo nobly furniſhed with all abiliments of a <hi>strong</hi> body, and <hi>valiant</hi> diſpoſition: as if victorious <hi>Ioſhua</hi> had <hi>revived</hi> to <hi>edge,</hi> theſe <hi>ill,</hi> &amp; <hi>dull,</hi> and <hi>reſty</hi> times, <hi>drowſed,</hi> and almoſt <hi>drowned</hi> in the ſweet <hi>have<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Peace, Peace</hi> being alienated from its own <hi>grace,</hi> and become the <hi>truce of lust,</hi> and <hi>rust of valour,</hi> the <hi>death</hi> of the <hi>army,</hi> and <hi>decay</hi> of the <hi>navie.</hi> And even then when this high borne <hi>Champion,</hi> the grace of the <hi>Court,</hi> and <hi>hope</hi> of the <hi>Campe,</hi> might haue recouered, if not improved the limits of this <hi>kingdome,</hi> when all good <hi>ſpirits</hi> not only <hi>affected,</hi> but <hi>addicted</hi> themſelues to <hi>honourable Martialiſme,</hi> expecting generally a day
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15628:8"/>wherein they might heare young <hi>Caeſars Venite,</hi> &amp; his <hi>brandiſhing ſword,</hi> the ioy of the <hi>ſouldier,</hi> drawne by <hi>right,</hi> edged by <hi>valour,</hi> might haue been attended with victorious acclamation of <hi>Conquest:</hi> even then, ſo did he <hi>ſeaſon</hi> &amp; <hi>ſanctifie</hi> his <hi>Martiall exerciſes,</hi> &amp; Princely <hi>studies</hi> of <hi>arts,</hi> and <hi>fortifications,</hi> that hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred the weapons of a <hi>Christian</hi> warfare, were not <hi>carnall</hi> but <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> and howſoever in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> he warred not after the <hi>fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.3.</note> 
               <hi>as the bleſsed Apoſtle doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, making that holy vſe of that vſefull knowledge of <hi>fortifications,</hi> as that he vſed them in a ſpirituall ſenſe, as S. <hi>Paule</hi> counſelleth, to the <hi>pulling downe of ſtrong holds, to the caſting downe of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, and every high thing that exalteth it ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the knowledge of God, bringing into captivity eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his thoughts to the obedience of Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.4.</note> 2. Cor. 10.4, 5 So did hee enter <hi>combat,</hi> and receaue <hi>conqueſt</hi> of both his <hi>enimies</hi> and <hi>himſelfe,</hi> and bare before him a <hi>ſhield</hi> which was never <hi>miſſed,</hi> yet never <hi>pierced.</hi> It was ſtrange in S. <hi>Ieroms</hi> opinion,<note place="margin">Hieron. in Ep. ad Theod.</note> 
               <hi>quod corpus aſſuetum tuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae potuit ſuſtinere onus Loricae,</hi> that the emblem of <hi>Arts,</hi> the <hi>Gowne,</hi> and the <hi>ornament</hi> of <hi>Armes, Armour,</hi> ſhould fit one &amp; the <hi>ſame;</hi> that ſo tender, Courtly, Princely breeding could afford ſo well ſet a ſoule, a <hi>body</hi> as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as able to haue endured the <hi>Laborious</hi> watching, toyling, fighting, bleeding life of a <hi>Campe.</hi> But that which is more wonder appeared in <hi>him,</hi> that the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> or <hi>vipers</hi> of a Courtly life, <hi>Luſt, Pride, Ambition, Irreligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> never durſt approch <hi>him,</hi> no nor the <hi>wormes</hi> or <hi>moaths</hi> of <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> ſloath, or <hi>flatterie,</hi> or <hi>vanitie</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15628:9"/>receaue <hi>acquaintance,</hi> much leſſe <hi>entertainement</hi> with him. All which <hi>creeping,</hi> or <hi>crying</hi> ſinnes, bee as <hi>viſible</hi> as <hi>indiviſible</hi> from ſuch Courtly places: which may bee ſome cauſe that the worde <hi>aula,</hi> which the <hi>Greeks</hi> tranſlate <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Athen.</note> is by <hi>Athenaeus</hi> interpreted to be <hi>perflatile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ventis domum;</hi> like the houſe in the <hi>Goſpell</hi> beaten with the <hi>winds,</hi> furious <hi>paſſion</hi> tearing, or cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>Ambition</hi> overturning, or envious <hi>contention</hi> breaking, or luſtfull <hi>daliance blaſting,</hi> as by violent <hi>ſtormes</hi> the <hi>faireſt</hi> and moſt <hi>hopefull</hi> fruites of <hi>Court</hi> &amp; <hi>kingdome,</hi> haue beene often, not onely <hi>blemiſhed</hi> but <hi>demoliſhed.</hi> That wee fitly might take vp for ſuch Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that Lamentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>David</hi> for <hi>Mount Gilboa,</hi> o yee <hi>Mountaines</hi> of <hi>Gilboa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sam. 1.19.21.23.</note> 
               <hi>how are the mighty fallen! how hath the beauty of Iſrael beene ſlaine vpon thy high places!</hi> they that were ſwifter then <hi>Eagles,</hi> ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger then <hi>Lyons</hi> are fallen in the midſt of thee, <hi>Pillers</hi> and <hi>Cedars</hi> in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> houſe haue ſunke downe even to the <hi>ground,</hi> &amp; yet this excellent <hi>Mirrour of Princes</hi> ſtood as a <hi>center</hi> vnmoved, &amp; retained his <hi>ſtation.</hi> His <hi>liberty</hi> more, <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities</hi> more, <hi>power</hi> more, &amp; <hi>incitations</hi> more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other <hi>great ones,</hi> yet he more <hi>free,</hi> becauſe more <hi>faith full</hi> then others, <hi>yea,</hi> ſo free that <hi>infernall</hi> malice, nor the <hi>curious</hi> inquiry of <hi>Popiſh</hi> Pioners could ever faſten any taint of <hi>blemiſh,</hi> either <hi>before</hi> or <hi>ſince</hi> his death, vpon his <hi>Saintlike</hi> life. I abhorre <hi>flattery,</hi> and dare call <hi>evill,</hi> evill, were it in <hi>Bethell</hi> the <hi>kings Chappell:</hi> let <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Courtier</hi> &amp; <hi>flatterer</hi> be the <hi>reciprocall tearmes</hi> of thoſe that <hi>tune</hi> their <hi>tongues</hi> to inchantments; I had rather be a Citizen of <hi>Verona</hi> then <hi>Placentia,</hi> and with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15628:9"/>
               <hi>S. Auſtin, mallem pati ſupplicium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ep. <hi>68.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quàm foedâ adulatione conſequi beneficium,</hi> I had rather endure <hi>puniſhment</hi> for <hi>truth,</hi> then get <hi>favour</hi> by <hi>flattery. Diogenes</hi> the <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke</hi> contemned it and ioined togither <hi>linguam adu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latoris &amp; manum interfectoris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diog in Laert,</note> and bleſſed <hi>Prince,</hi> who now is in heaven, in his life <hi>laughed flattery</hi> to ſcorne, and held that as the <hi>Tyrant</hi> among the wilde, ſo the flatterer among tame beaſts is moſt pernitious. It may be <hi>Aulica Rhetorica,</hi> to giue more then is due to great ones in their <hi>life,</hi> but that <hi>candle</hi> being extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed how buſie are <hi>tongues</hi> and <hi>pens</hi> to breake open the <hi>ſepulchers</hi> of the <hi>deceaſed,</hi> a thing more <hi>common</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>commendable</hi> in this age. But to giue the ampleſt <hi>testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> of <hi>truth</hi> as wel as of <hi>affection, Teſtimonia virtutis &amp; veritatis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> is an office in <hi>S. Bernards</hi> iudgement that we are bound vnto, <hi>Piety</hi> as well as <hi>duty</hi> requireth it, &amp; <hi>quitteth</hi> herein <hi>flattery,</hi> that a <hi>ſea</hi> man whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is come to the <hi>haven,</hi> and a warriour when he is brought to <hi>his triumph,</hi> and the <hi>bleſſed</hi> that die in the <hi>Lord</hi> and reſt from their <hi>labors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 14.</note> they that haue been the great <hi>lights</hi> of our firmament their <hi>works</hi> following them, <hi>propter opera &amp; exempla accipiant benigna hominum verba &amp; iudicia,</hi> may be honoured in the <hi>monuments</hi> of their <hi>memorials</hi> by iuſt praiſes, not iſſuing from <hi>Hypocriſy</hi> or <hi>flattery,</hi> to neglect which <hi>ſervice,</hi> were <hi>prophane ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude,</hi> or to <hi>deride</hi> it <hi>impious preſumption.</hi> For, to any honeſt minde, how <hi>vnworthy</hi> will it ſeeme to <hi>deny,</hi> or <hi>maligne</hi> vertue its due, which ſo abundantly, did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in this <hi>triumphant Saint,</hi> the living <hi>glory</hi> of the <hi>Protestant,</hi> and riſing <hi>envy</hi> of the <hi>malignant</hi> world, as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15628:10"/>if the <hi>Graces</hi> had beene <hi>midwiues</hi> at his <hi>birth,</hi> the <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> his <hi>nurſes,</hi> the <hi>vertues</hi> his <hi>attendants,</hi> and <hi>goodneſſe</hi> as a good <hi>Angell,</hi> his <hi>guide</hi> to direct him in al his <hi>waies.</hi> And as if acquainted with <hi>Saturne</hi> the Planet of <hi>Conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation,</hi> and with <hi>Iupiter</hi> the Planet of <hi>Action</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Quaerere.</note> 
               <hi>Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere</hi> was the word <hi>beſt</hi> liked him, the <hi>worke</hi> that beſt <hi>fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him.</hi> As if he had duly conſidered our Saviours councell, <hi>Primù quaerite,</hi> firſt ſeeke; <hi>Cum dicit quaerite en diligentiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6 33.</note> 
               <hi>cum primùm quaerite en ſapientiam, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> in <hi>ſeeking,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> 
               <hi>wiſdome</hi> in <hi>ſeeking firſt.</hi> It was the fruit of both, in <hi>Ioſias</hi> to <hi>beginne to ſeeke God the firſt time of his raigne</hi> when he was a <hi>childe,</hi> in <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> to come to the <hi>ſepulcher</hi> the <hi>firſt day</hi> of the <hi>weeke</hi> before the <hi>dawning</hi> of the day, in thoſe that were <hi>firſt</hi> admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the <hi>vineyard,</hi> that they were in the <hi>market</hi> the firſt <hi>howre</hi> the Maſter came to hire; the <hi>firſtlings</hi> of the <hi>cattell, firſt borne</hi> of the <hi>children, first fruits</hi> of the <hi>earth, firſt hopes</hi> of the <hi>promiſe, firſt</hi> tythes of the <hi>yeere,</hi> &amp; <hi>firſt times</hi> of the day were ever <hi>deere</hi> &amp; <hi>acceptable</hi> to God. To <hi>inſtance</hi> in the <hi>laſt</hi> only, the firſt <hi>opening</hi> of the <hi>daie,</hi> ſeeing, there is no <hi>word</hi> vnneceſſary in the <hi>book of God,</hi> every iot <hi>therein,</hi> affording <hi>obſervation,</hi> if not <hi>Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> why ſo <hi>preciſely</hi> is this time of the day the <hi>morning</hi> mentioned in <hi>ſcripture?</hi> the <hi>Angels</hi> haſtning <hi>Lot</hi> out of <hi>Sodom</hi> in the morning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Gen. 19.15. <hi>Abraham</hi> his preparation by riſing <hi>earely</hi> to go to <hi>ſacrifice Iſaac</hi> in the <hi>morning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19.15.</note> Gen. 22.3. <hi>Iacob</hi> to ſet vp a <hi>piller</hi> at <hi>Bethel</hi> roſe vp earely in the <hi>morning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 22.3.</note> Gen. 28.18. <hi>Moſes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to ſtand before <hi>Pharao</hi> earely in the <hi>morning,</hi> Exod. 9.15. <hi>Ioſhua</hi> in his care in the conviction of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chan</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:15628:10"/>roſe vp earely in the <hi>morning,</hi> Ioſh. 7.16. <hi>Elkanah</hi> and <hi>Hannah</hi> their earely <hi>worſhip,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 1.9. 1. Chr. 33.30. Iob. 1.2. Chr. 31.3. Ier. 17.13.</note> the <hi>Levits</hi> early ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding before the <hi>Lord, Iob</hi> early ſanctifying of his <hi>ſons, Hezekias</hi> early <hi>ſacrificing, David</hi> early <hi>praying, Ieremy</hi> early <hi>preaching,</hi> and Chriſt early <hi>riſing,</hi> with infinite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>examples</hi> of the <hi>morning</hi> ſervice that the Saints haue <hi>perfourmed.</hi> I ſay wherefore is this eſpeciall <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance</hi> ſo exactly <hi>placed</hi> in the <hi>front of</hi> ſo many of the ſacred <hi>hiſtories,</hi> if it did not note vnto <hi>vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquin.</note> how <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable the firſt fruit</hi> of time is vnto the <hi>Lord,</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore firſt to <hi>ſeeke,</hi> in the beginning of our <hi>day,</hi> whether as <hi>Thomas</hi> diſtinguiſheth, it bee in the morning of the <hi>naturall</hi> day, or of our <hi>humane</hi> life, or of <hi>our ſtate in grace,</hi> or <hi>paſſage</hi> to glory, the <hi>Prime</hi> of our <hi>Calender</hi> to be conſecrated to <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>ſun</hi> no ſooner to <hi>diſplay</hi> its light vpon the <hi>earth,</hi> then we to lift our <hi>ſoules</hi> vnto the <hi>heaven.</hi> As was the <hi>dayly</hi> and early courſe of this devout <hi>Prince,</hi> who in his private morning prayer, early ſeeking the God of his Fathers, communed with his own heart in his chamber, and was ſtill.<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.4.</note> It was a gratious <hi>promiſe</hi> made in the time of the Law, <hi>If thou ſeeke the Lord thy God, thou ſhalt find him,</hi> Deut. 4.29. &amp; ever ſince it hath beene the <hi>precept,</hi> or rather the ſum of all precepts to ſeeke the Lord, as appeareth by the <hi>Phraſe</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> either <hi>faciem quaerendo,</hi> by ſeeking his face, Pſal. 24.6. or <hi>bonitatem quaerendo,</hi> by ſeeking his goodneſſe, Eſra. 8.22. Or <hi>mandata quaerendo,</hi> by ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his Commandements, Pſal. 119.100. Or <hi>miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiam quaerendo.</hi> Dan. 2.18. &amp;c. and the <hi>bleſſing</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed is, that the <hi>hearts of them ſhall reioyce that ſeeke
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15628:11"/>the Lord,</hi> 1. Chr. 16.10. <hi>Yea the hearts of them ſhall liue that ſeeke the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 69.32. Which made the <hi>Royall Pſalmiſt</hi> ſo experimented, that he proclaimeth, they that knowe thy name will put their truſt in <hi>thee, for thou O Lord never faileſt them that ſeeke thee,</hi> Pſal. 9.10. Which may ſerue as a briefe <hi>application</hi> to all his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgements of deliverance, from the <hi>paw</hi> of the <hi>beare,</hi> the <hi>Iaw</hi> of the <hi>Lion,</hi> the <hi>Iauelin</hi> of <hi>Saul, Goliahs</hi> ſpeare, <hi>Achitophels</hi> trappe, <hi>Abſolons</hi> treaſon, <hi>Doegs</hi> ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>Shemei</hi> his curſe, from the mouth of the <hi>ſword,</hi> the <hi>murren</hi> of his people, the <hi>horrours</hi> of his ſinnes, &amp; the <hi>rebellion</hi> of his owne ſonnes. S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the Pſalmes asketh the queſtion vpon <hi>Davids ſpeech, Quaerite faciem eius ſemper; Si ſemper quaeritur, quando invenitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſalm.</note> 
               <hi>inventus eſt, &amp; tamen quaerendus eſt?</hi> Seeke his face evermore? why if he muſt bee ſought <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermore,</hi> when ſhall he be <hi>found,</hi> is he found, and yet is he to be <hi>ſought?</hi> and anſwereth <hi>himſelfe</hi> thus, <hi>Deum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venit fides &amp; adhuc eum quaerit ſpes, charit as autem &amp; invenit eum per fidem &amp; eum habere quaerit per ſpem,</hi> faith hath found <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>hope</hi> ſeeketh him, but <hi>charitie</hi> both hath found him by <hi>faith,</hi> and ſeeketh to <hi>haue</hi> him by <hi>hope.</hi> According to the meaſure of which methode our now <hi>Immortall,</hi> then <hi>mortall Prince,</hi> did ſeeke the <hi>Lord,</hi> being <hi>stedfaſt</hi> in faith, <hi>ioyfull</hi> through <hi>hope,</hi> &amp; roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>charitie;</hi> hee hath paſſed the waues of this trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome <hi>world,</hi> and is come to the <hi>Land</hi> of everlaſting <hi>life,</hi> and there hath found the <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Learne</hi> hence then from the <hi>Cedar</hi> yee fir trees, and <hi>ſhrubs</hi> of the <hi>forreſt,</hi> yee that ever lived vnder his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15628:11"/>
               <hi>ſhadow,</hi> or now are in the <hi>ſunſhine</hi> and <hi>countenance</hi> of greatneſſe, <hi>learne</hi> to ſeeke the <hi>Lord:</hi> this is the whole duty of man, the ſumme of all Gods will revealed in his <hi>word.</hi> Yee may ſee in the naturall agents, whether they be to <hi>beare rule,</hi> as the <hi>Sunne</hi> and <hi>Moone,</hi> which are placed in the <hi>firmament,</hi> or be <hi>ruled,</hi> as the <hi>Elements</hi> and parts of this lower world, they all worke, as if they knewe what they wrought, and in their ſeverall courſes ſeeke to performe his will, as if they were <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted</hi> with his <hi>wil.</hi> How much more doth it <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerne</hi> men, whom in a maner hee hath made partakers of the <hi>divine</hi> nature, to <hi>ſeeke</hi> his glory, ſeeing that by his glory, they ſeeke their own good? The <hi>Orbes</hi> &amp; <hi>Arches</hi> of heaven, with their <hi>ſtarres</hi> and <hi>planets,</hi> and the whole <hi>fabricke</hi> of nature, were ordained to finiſh their courſe by <hi>motions</hi> and <hi>operation:</hi> and ſo man as hee was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a <hi>more,</hi> nay to the <hi>moſt,</hi> happy and bleſſed ende, ſhould attaine therevnto, not by <hi>ſloath</hi> and <hi>idleneſſe,</hi> which (as the <hi>worme</hi> in the <hi>guord</hi>) be the <hi>devourers</hi> of <hi>goodneſſe;</hi> but by <hi>endeavour</hi> which is the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and by ambition the <hi>ſpurre,</hi> ſhould ſtirre on in the waies of <hi>grace,</hi> being in the glorious <hi>liberties</hi> of the ſonnes of God. How commonly knowne be thoſe notions, that our life is but a <hi>iourney,</hi> a <hi>race,</hi> a <hi>votage,</hi> a <hi>combat,</hi> &amp; we are but <hi>travellers, ſouldiers, workemen</hi> in the vineyard, &amp;c. All which are with many more notes of <hi>ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> and <hi>labouring,</hi> which ſhould <hi>edge</hi> a good minde to wiſh as <hi>Heathen Seneca</hi> did,<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> that hee might ever bee in action, <hi>Malo enim</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>vt me fortuna in caſtris ſuis, quàm in delitijs habeat,</hi> hee had rather bee <hi>fortunes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15628:12"/>warriour</hi> then her <hi>wanton,</hi> &amp; rather dwell in her <hi>Camp</hi> then in her <hi>Court. Eraſmus profeſſeth</hi> that hee had no time to be ſicke, or opportunitie to take Phyſicke: and the former <hi>Seneca,</hi> that he had ſcarſe leaſure to ſleepe, <hi>Nullus mihi per otium dies exit, partem noctium ſtudijs vendico,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen. Ep. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>non vaco ſomno, &amp;c.</hi> neither <hi>day</hi> nor <hi>night,</hi> ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or <hi>ſleeping</hi> could withdrawe him from ſtudies; &amp; the deviſe of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> who by letting a ball fall into a <hi>baſon,</hi> kept himſelfe waking. Which <hi>ſtarre-light</hi> of good in them ſhould ſtirre vs vp, who are in the <hi>ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of grace,</hi> &amp; lead vs on to the <hi>ſearch</hi> and diſcovery of <hi>Immortalitie.</hi> Theſe <hi>meditations</hi> ſhould lead vs on further to the Queene of the <hi>South,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 10.</note> ſeeking by a long iourny to come to heare <hi>Solomon:</hi> ſhee and the <hi>Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vits,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> and other <hi>Heathens,</hi> may iuſtly ariſe in iudgement againſt this <hi>generation,</hi> and condemne vs <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> For not to flatter our ſelues in a matter of ſo great importance, wee cannot plead <hi>ignorance,</hi> neither can we excuſe <hi>negligence,</hi> in the care of our <hi>ſearching,</hi> and maner of our <hi>ſeeking.</hi> The devouring <hi>ſword,</hi> terrible <hi>ſhot,</hi> wounds, outcries, alarmes, groanes of the <hi>dying,</hi> danger of the <hi>ſurviving,</hi> cannot keep the valiant war riour from ſeeking the lawrell of <hi>victories.</hi> The vnta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Sea,</hi> and tottering <hi>ſhip,</hi> the <hi>ſtormes,</hi> or <hi>calmes,</hi> or <hi>rocks,</hi> or <hi>ſands,</hi> or <hi>ſhipwracke</hi> of others cannot detain the Marriner from ſeeking for his hoped for <hi>commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities.</hi> And yet the one in the height of his <hi>honour</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his way through blood, and the other, as if borne vnder <hi>Aquarius</hi> waſts his life in the <hi>waters:</hi> whereas many, whoſe whole life never partakes of any painful
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15628:12"/>
               <hi>interruption,</hi> whoſe bellie God hath filled with <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> and ſatisfied with all maner of <hi>content,</hi> haue not begunne to ſeeke, nor cared to finde the God of their <hi>Fathers;</hi> thinking it then time enough, when the cloud of <hi>ſickneſſe</hi> portendeth the <hi>Tempeſt</hi> of death, which like a da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe puts out al the <hi>light</hi> of <hi>pleaſure.</hi> How deere therefore ought that <hi>counſell</hi> to bee, Seeke the Lord while he may be found, <hi>(i)</hi> to ſeeke him while we may ſeeke him: for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Time is fixed on a wheele,<note place="margin">Athe.</note> that inceſſantly whirleth, and draweth with it vs, &amp; all our actions. And our <hi>leaſe</hi> of life is, as the ancient <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes</hi> haue by calculation of the yeares obſerved, ſo ſhort, that if wee would with all our <hi>forces</hi> and <hi>studies</hi> endeavour to atchieue ſome matter of worth, wee ſhould bee in daunger of wanting <hi>day light.</hi> For if the daies of our age be <hi>threeſcore</hi> yeares and ten, or if men bee ſo ſtrong that they come to <hi>foureſcore,</hi> which was the longeſt date of yeares that <hi>Moſes</hi> afforded;<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.10.</note> deduct firſt the time of <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>ſleeping,</hi> which is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>moetie of mans life;</hi> &amp; then deduct the daies of <hi>child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> which is an <hi>ignorant folly, and innocent ſimplicitie,</hi> then deduct the daies of <hi>youth,</hi> which is no better then and <hi>indiſcreet heat, raſh</hi> and <hi>heady,</hi> and as <hi>Solomon</hi> calleth it, an inconſtant vanitie; deduct yet the daies of <hi>age, which is lifes wast, and mans winter, a hoare froſt, cold and vnhealthy:</hi> and when wee thinke this <hi>Survey</hi> and <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction</hi> is ended, and we haue ſeene all the travel, that God hath giuen vnto the <hi>Sonnes</hi> of men, to bee exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed therein; yet deduct the daies of <hi>Sorrowe,</hi> the ſouls <hi>feaver,</hi> an eating <hi>viper,</hi> a fainting <hi>miſerie,</hi> a little colde
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15628:13"/>to pinch vs, a little heat to <hi>parch</hi> vs, the aking of a <hi>tooth</hi> or <hi>finger,</hi> able to diſtract our <hi>ſtudies,</hi> or <hi>ſports,</hi> or <hi>labors;</hi> in <hi>ſickneſſe weake,</hi> in <hi>diſcontent withered:</hi> and all theſe houres of <hi>childhood, youth, age, ſleepe, ſickneſſe, ſorrowe, ſubſtracted,</hi> where is that life of man threeſcore yeares &amp; ten? Which if it were ful, it were but the number of the yeares of <hi>Babylòs</hi> captivity. Nay where is the <hi>yeare,</hi> the <hi>day,</hi> the <hi>houre,</hi> that man may be ſaid to liue? The life of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is but a ſpa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> long, nay leſſe, it is but <hi>inſtans te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poris,</hi> a moment. <hi>Number &amp; weigh</hi> the time paſt, it is ſpent, it <hi>weighs nothing. Number</hi> and <hi>weigh</hi> the time to <hi>come,</hi> it is <hi>vncertaine,</hi> we cannot weigh it. <hi>Number &amp; weigh</hi> the time <hi>preſent,</hi> is is not a <hi>dram,</hi> a <hi>graine,</hi> a <hi>mite,</hi> it is but a <hi>moment. Eudaeus, Villalpanda,</hi> nor all the <hi>meaſuriſts</hi> haue <hi>waight</hi> or <hi>meaſure</hi> to expreſſe ſuch a <hi>fragment,</hi> a <hi>moment,</hi> being not ſo much in <hi>proportion</hi> to <hi>eternity</hi> as the leaſt moat in the <hi>aire,</hi> to the body of the whole <hi>earth.</hi> Wherefore, if God, even beyond the courſe of the <hi>natural compaſse</hi> of life do vouchſafe thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath choſen from the world, &amp; called out of the <hi>world</hi> to endow them with the life of <hi>grace,</hi> to the end they may <hi>ſeeke</hi> his <hi>glory,</hi> and even in the frailtie of <hi>life</hi> to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford many ſo bleſſed &amp; <hi>gratious</hi> opportunities to ſeek him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let vs gird vp our <hi>loines,</hi> and ſeeing the <hi>day ſtarre</hi> hath ſhined in our <hi>hearts,</hi> and the day ſprang from on <hi>high</hi> hath viſited vs, <hi>let vs runne with patience vnto the race that is ſet before vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note> looking, ſeeking, ſtriving, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly endeavouring, and preſſing hard to the marke, vnto <hi>Ieſus</hi> the author, and finiſher of our faith; whom if we <hi>ſeeke</hi> we ſhall <hi>finde,</hi> and with him all things <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:15628:13"/>for vs. To which glorious acquiſition as this <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Prince</hi> was faithfully <hi>addicted,</hi> ſo now is he of it, in ſoule, fully <hi>poſseſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 Whoſe noble <hi>thoughts</hi> aymed at more, then either his Royall birth could deſigne <hi>him,</hi> or <hi>Regal</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion aſſure him, deſiring to <hi>improue</hi> his <hi>Patrimonie:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Regna extera.</note> 
               <hi>Regna extera,</hi> that is, <hi>coelica Regna,</hi> or<note n="*" place="margin">Pithagorei vocant <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ex adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Terram. Clem. Alex. Strom. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. vlt.</note> 
               <hi>Regna extera quaerere</hi> that is, <hi>Regna ex terra,</hi> or <hi>extra terram;</hi> celeſtial kingdomes, were his <hi>aime,</hi> &amp; <hi>hope,</hi> a <hi>kingdome</hi> that hath no <hi>end</hi> for <hi>termination,</hi> no <hi>confines</hi> for <hi>limitation,</hi> farre aboue <hi>principalities</hi> and <hi>powers,</hi> wherein no man can <hi>reſolue</hi> whether his ſanctified <hi>ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> were more <hi>high</hi> or more <hi>happy.</hi> For had his deſires level'd, at the <hi>regai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> of a <hi>neighbour</hi> kingdome, which either by match hath beene <hi>conioyned</hi> or by <hi>proweſse</hi> hath beene <hi>conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> the <hi>example</hi> had not wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted <hi>followers,</hi> nor the <hi>enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe honours.</hi> Our Chronicles haue <hi>bequeathed</hi> a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony vnto al poſterity in this kinde of a * renowmed Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> whoſe <hi>honour ſhall not lie in the dust,<note n="*" place="margin">The victorious Blacke Prince.</note>
               </hi> while the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>light</hi> of books, ſhall remaine whoſe much <hi>honoured example,</hi> no doubt, did much adde <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,</hi> to Great HENRIES diſpoſition of <hi>warlike honor,</hi> in the <hi>atchieving</hi> of ſome Princely <hi>adventure,</hi> and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving life to that <hi>honourable,</hi> though now <hi>lamentable</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of <hi>Engliſh Martialiſts.</hi> Whoſe <hi>valiant ſervice,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Turkiſh</hi> enemies, hath beene <hi>ſealed</hi> with their <hi>blood,</hi> and they had in high <hi>eſteeme</hi> among al the <hi>military</hi> men in the <hi>world,</hi> whoſe renowne had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed a <hi>reſurrection,</hi> had this <hi>Loadſtarre</hi> of <hi>honour</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared longer. But his <hi>deſignes</hi> being directed to a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15628:14"/>more <hi>ſpirituall marke,</hi> heaven was his <hi>hope,</hi> beginning his <hi>voiage</hi> to <hi>glory</hi> in the way of <hi>grace:</hi> through which kingdome <hi>of grace</hi> he paſſed, not as an <hi>alien,</hi> or <hi>travei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> but as an <hi>inheritour,</hi> not as a <hi>ſervant</hi> but as a Prince ly <hi>ſonne,</hi> an heire, a coheire, acquainted in his paſſage, with <hi>the word,</hi> and accompanied with the Angels of <hi>God.</hi> Seeing al worldly things, <hi>beneath</hi> him, he <hi>eſteemed</hi> them as <hi>ſublunary,</hi> neither altogither worthy of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt,</hi> nor any way as able to afford <hi>content</hi> to his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which like an <hi>Eagle</hi> fled vp into the <hi>ſpheare</hi> of divine <hi>contemplation:</hi> and ſo farre was he aboue his <hi>nature</hi> by <hi>grace,</hi> as hee was by <hi>Royall birth</hi> in <hi>nature</hi> aboue <hi>other men.</hi> A <hi>kingdome</hi> he might haue affected: for world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>honours ſanctified,</hi> may be <hi>ſought</hi> by thoſe <hi>whom</hi> God hath <hi>therevnto</hi> appointed.<note place="margin">Gen. 49.1.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob</hi> beſides his legacie of <hi>ſpirituall bleſſing,</hi> left temporall <hi>legacies</hi> to his ſonnes, the <hi>bleſſing</hi> of the Sea to <hi>Zabulon,</hi> bleſſing of fruits of the land to <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> Iudgement to <hi>Dan,</hi> victory to <hi>Gad,</hi> ſtaffe of bread to <hi>Aſher,</hi> Eloquence to <hi>Nepthali,</hi> fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> the ſcepter to <hi>Iudah,</hi> &amp; ſo of the reſt. And it was <hi>Davids</hi> acknowledgement, <hi>The king ſhall reioice in thy ſtrength O Lord, exceeding glad ſhall he bee of thy ſalvation. Thou haſt given him his hearts deſire, &amp; haſt not denyed him the request of his lips.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 21.3.</note> 
               <hi>Thou hast pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented him with the bleſſings of goodneſse, thou haſt ſet a crowne of pure gold vpon his head,</hi> Pſal. 21.3. When the kingly Prophet confeſſeth with much ioy the <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings</hi> he had received from the <hi>Lord</hi> generally here as in other places, <hi>particularly</hi> hee nameth theſe <hi>bleſſings</hi> of good things, how he was <hi>choſen before</hi> his brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15628:14"/>
               <hi>wiſer</hi> then his <hi>teachers, worthyer</hi> then the <hi>ancients, ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> then his <hi>enemies,</hi> and not only <hi>expreſseth</hi> God to be the <hi>author</hi> of his <hi>Royall power,</hi> but alſo of his <hi>Martiall proweſſe, Bleſſed be the Lord my ſtrength, which teacheth my hands to war and my fingers to fight, my goodnes, my fortreſſe, my tower, my deliverer, my ſhield,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 140.1.</note> Pſal. 140.1. Yea and the preſervations of him <hi>in vtero, ex vtero, ab vtero,</hi> to <hi>bring him</hi> to that <hi>dignity,</hi> by <hi>covering</hi> him in his <hi>mothers wombe,</hi> Pſal. 139.13. by receiving him from the <hi>wombe,</hi> Pſal. 22.10. yea <hi>by taking</hi> him out of the <hi>wombe,</hi> Pſal. 71.6. All religious <hi>Princes</hi> will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>Tuum eſt regnum Potentia &amp; gloria:</hi> his was the <hi>Practique</hi> well as the <hi>Theorique,</hi> he put kingdomes in the ſcales <hi>of iudgement</hi> to examine as wel the <hi>weight</hi> of their <hi>worth</hi> &amp; Gods bleſſing in ſo great <hi>gifts,</hi> as the weight of their <hi>labyrinths</hi> of cares, &amp; feares, and <hi>Mae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anders</hi> of <hi>troubles;</hi> he found the <hi>honours</hi> to be <hi>tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> that good kings were the <hi>Dearlings</hi> of God, his <hi>deputies, ſtars</hi> in his <hi>hands, ſignets</hi> on his <hi>finger,</hi> the great <hi>lights</hi> of his <hi>firmament;</hi> thoſe, to whom he not onlie <hi>partaked</hi> his <hi>ſcepter,</hi> his <hi>power,</hi> his <hi>honour,</hi> but even of his owne <hi>omnipotent</hi> Titles, not only as the woman of <hi>Tekoa</hi> gaue the attribute to <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 14.17.</note> 
               <hi>My Lorde the king is wiſe, as an Angell of God,</hi> but God beſtowing his owne name, <hi>Dixi quod Dij eſtis,</hi> I haue ſaid yee are Gods, Pſal. 82. and his ſons name, <hi>Nolite tangere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtos meos,</hi> Touch not my Chriſts, Pſal. 105. and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>name,</hi> but the power and ſpeech of his <hi>ſpirit,</hi> as in <hi>David, Spiritus Domini loquutus eſt per me,</hi> the ſpirit of the Lord hath ſpoken by me, 2. Sam. 23.2. and, that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15628:15"/>they haue ever <hi>beene eſteemed</hi> the <hi>chiefest</hi> of the <hi>ſonnes</hi> of men, the <hi>chariots</hi> of <hi>Iſrael, Oracles</hi> of wiſdome, <hi>Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions</hi> of valour, <hi>Guardians</hi> of Iuſtice, the <hi>Gemmes</hi> &amp; <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>adems</hi> of governments beauty. <hi>Yet,</hi> in al this <hi>Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty,</hi> they are ſubiect to more <hi>violence</hi> of <hi>ſtorme,</hi> then their <hi>ſubiects,</hi> they are no more free from <hi>emptineſse, wearyneſſe, thirst, heate, cold, ſweat, labour.</hi> They are like the heavenly <hi>bodies,</hi> which cauſe <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evill</hi> times, which haue much <hi>reſpect</hi> and no <hi>reſt,</hi> ever in <hi>motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver freed in their <hi>perſons, actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> or <hi>times;</hi> being in <hi>great</hi> ſtate, they are <hi>greateſt</hi> ſtrangers to themſelues, &amp; haue (if they duely execute their <hi>great places</hi>) ſmal time to attend the <hi>health</hi> ether of <hi>body</hi> or <hi>minde.</hi> Nay more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others their provident watchfulneſſe expreſſed in the Aegyptian <hi>Hierogliphicke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pier. Hierog.</note> 
               <hi>ſceptrum cum oculo</hi> ſhe weth that day nor night, any <hi>intermiſsion</hi> ſhould exclude their <hi>cares,</hi> for the <hi>ſtate</hi> they governe, by the <hi>influence</hi> of their goodneſſe: ſeeing as the dignity, ſo the burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of duty is ſo great, as that <hi>Seneca</hi> his ſpeech vpon this <hi>occaſion</hi> is found moſt true,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quis quámne regno gaudet? O fallax bonum,</l>
               <l>Quantum malorum, quàm fronte blandâ tegis!</l>
            </q>
            <p>The beſt of <hi>Kings</hi> findes, that ſometimes <hi>hee weares a Crowne of thornes. Coronets</hi> and <hi>Chapplets</hi> of <hi>Oliues,</hi> or <hi>Lillies,</hi> or <hi>Lawrels,</hi> or <hi>Roſes,</hi> or <hi>Violets,</hi> or <hi>Gold,</hi> or <hi>Pearle,</hi> are not without ſomewhat that will often <hi>vexe</hi> the <hi>wearers,</hi> and they will confeſſe that within that ſmall <hi>circle</hi> there is the weight of a <hi>world.</hi> The boyſtrous troubles attending on which cauſed the <hi>heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that if a Crowne lay before him on the <hi>ground,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:15628:15"/>he would not thinke it worth the <hi>taking vp; Caſſiodor</hi> confirming that by the neglect of the <hi>heathen, Regnum est, nolle regnare.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caſſiod. Ep. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> And therefore did our <hi>Bleſsed Prince</hi> lay his proiect for a <hi>kingdome,</hi> out of <hi>compaſse</hi> of <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> or <hi>treaſon.</hi> Howſoever by the dues of <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>cuſtome,</hi> and <hi>ſucceſſion</hi> hee was haire apparant to three <hi>Crownes,</hi> yet hee tooke vp the <hi>motto</hi> of that Reverend<note n="*" place="margin">S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Thomas Bodley.</note> 
               <hi>Centurion,</hi> who built vs a <hi>Synagogue, Quarta Perennis,</hi> and moſt divinely conſidered, that an earthly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was like the place, where <hi>Paule</hi> reſted called the <hi>faire havens,</hi> Act. 27.8. yet <hi>Eur oclydon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 27.8.</note> a tempeſtuous eaſterly winde may ariſe, no ſafetie in a <hi>kings Palace,</hi> be it never ſo <hi>strong:</hi> not in his dining Chamber, <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzar</hi> was aſtoniſhed there; nor in that <hi>Privy</hi> cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <hi>Eglon</hi> was ſlaine there; nor in the <hi>bed chamber Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſheth</hi> was ſlaughtered there; nor in the <hi>Chappell, Ze<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacherib</hi> was murthered there: <hi>Only,</hi> ſafetie is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pected <hi>there, where never harme entred in, ſince Sathan was put out,</hi> where there is a <hi>kingdome,</hi> where the <hi>Prince</hi> is <hi>veritie,</hi> the <hi>Lawes Charitie,</hi> and the limits <hi>Eternitie,</hi> where the meat is <hi>Manna,</hi> the exerciſe <hi>reioycing,</hi> the muſicke <hi>Haleluiah,</hi> the company <hi>Saints,</hi> and the Quire <hi>Angels.</hi> Not only a kingdome of <hi>Priests,</hi> as in Exod. 19.6. or a kingdome of <hi>Prophets,</hi> as in Luk. 13.28. but a kingdome of <hi>kings,</hi> Rev. 1.5. but a <hi>prepared</hi> kingdom Mat. 25.34. A <hi>heavenly</hi> kingdome, 2. Tim. 4.18. An <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall</hi> kingdome, 2. Pet. 1.11. The <hi>kingdome</hi> of heaven Mat. 18.3. The <hi>kingdome</hi> of Chriſt, Eph. 5.5. The <hi>king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of God, Ioh. 3.3. A <hi>kingdome</hi> where there is <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> and <hi>glory.</hi> Into which <hi>kingdome, power</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15628:16"/>
               <hi>triumphant Saint,</hi> bleſſed Prince <hi>Henry</hi> is already en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and having kept his <hi>faith,</hi> fought his <hi>fight,</hi> ran his <hi>race,</hi> and finiſhed his <hi>courſe,</hi> he hath obtained a <hi>Crowne</hi> laid vp for him, the Crown of <hi>life,</hi> Iam. 1.12. a Crown of <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> 1. Tim. 4. an <hi>immarceſſible</hi> Crowne of <hi>Glory,</hi> 1. Pet. 5.4.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Learne hence yee dunghill <hi>muckwormes,</hi> whoſe baſe earthly and <hi>beaſtly</hi> thoughts never ſtraine further then to be <hi>ambitious</hi> of <hi>Mammon,</hi> and to lay vp trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure where the <hi>ruſt</hi> and <hi>moath</hi> doth corrupt &amp; where theeues do breake in, and ſteale; never partaking <hi>anie ſparke</hi> of a <hi>noble ſpirit,</hi> whoſe ſoule is not only <hi>encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged,</hi> but <hi>enraged</hi> &amp; <hi>enflamed</hi> with the deſire of a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. How ought this ambition of the ſoule, to be of force, to <hi>darken</hi> and <hi>dull</hi> all ſenſuall <hi>ſenſes</hi> &amp; world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>regards,</hi> and to carry yee vp, vpon the wings of <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire</hi> and <hi>hope,</hi> that yee may performe <hi>the paſſage</hi> with more <hi>alacrity,</hi> to come to this <hi>kingdome:</hi> that when ye are no longer capable of <hi>this world</hi> ye may bee <hi>establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed</hi> in a kingdome of moſt happy <hi>condition.</hi> It was the ſpeech of <hi>Philip</hi> to his ſonne <hi>Alexander, Idoneum &amp; compar tibiregnum fili invenias, quoniam Macedonia tui capax no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt,</hi> Sonne ſeeing <hi>Macedonia</hi> is not a place <hi>fit</hi> for thee, thou maiſt finde a more <hi>competible</hi> and <hi>capacious</hi> kingdome. The <hi>world</hi> is not capable of <hi>vs,</hi> it is a limited finite ſmall <hi>compaſſe,</hi> the <hi>ſoule</hi> though it be but the inmate of the <hi>body,</hi> is a celeſtiall <hi>tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent creature,</hi> and being rightly guided, is ever aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>vpwards,</hi> not here tranſported, either with <hi>deſire</hi> of that which ſhee <hi>hath not,</hi> or with <hi>carnall delight</hi> of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15628:16"/>that ſhee <hi>hath,</hi> never entertaining at one time and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, thoſe two <hi>extreames,</hi> the <hi>loue</hi> of God and of the <hi>world;</hi> her <hi>ſingle eie</hi> not being able to behold <hi>heaven,</hi> and <hi>earth togither,</hi> and therefore neglecteth <hi>riches</hi> as a <hi>thorne, pleaſure</hi> as a <hi>ſpurre, glory</hi> as a <hi>blaſt, beauty</hi> as a <hi>flowre, luſt</hi> as a <hi>fire,</hi> and <hi>Ioy</hi> as a <hi>fury.</hi> It was <hi>Cyrus</hi> procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to animate his <hi>army,</hi> and to draw <hi>valiant</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to his <hi>party,</hi> that, whoſoever would ſerue him in that <hi>warre</hi> ſhould worthily be <hi>preferred,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut in vitae Pyrrbi.</note> whatſoever his condition were. If he poſſeſſed a <hi>Cottage,</hi> he would giue him a <hi>village;</hi> If he had a <hi>village</hi> he ſhould be <hi>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour</hi> of a City; if <hi>Ruler</hi> of a City he would make him Prince of a <hi>Region,</hi> or <hi>king</hi> of ſome <hi>Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try.</hi> What he promiſed to the beſt of <hi>his, God</hi> proclaimeth to the leaſt of his even a <hi>kingdome,</hi> even a <hi>kingdome</hi> of ſuch <hi>maieſtie,</hi> that neither in <hi>deſire</hi> this ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wiſh, nor in hope <hi>aſpire,</hi> nor in imagination <hi>faine</hi> any greater glory. What empty and ſpungy creatures then be they, who deſire to ſatisfie their fill with any thing, and beſtowe all their liues in ſeeking onely thoſe things, which be wiſht <hi>ſine providentia,</hi> and kept <hi>non ſine poenitentia.</hi> What fruit can appeare in thoſe things, <hi>Quae poſſeſſa o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in <hi>119.</hi> Pſ.</note> 
               <hi>amata inquinant, amiſſa cruciant,</hi> in poſſeſſing wherof they <hi>burden,</hi> in louing whereof they <hi>defile,</hi> in looſing whereof they <hi>torment</hi> themſelues. S. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> fitly propoſeth a great man in the higheſt <hi>ſpheare</hi> of earthly <hi>Elevation,</hi> and thus beſpeaketh him, <hi>O man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> 
               <hi>Is es quem ſenſus fallit, tempus deſerit, &amp;c.</hi> Thou art hee whom <hi>ſenſe</hi> deceaueth, and time forſaketh, whome <hi>Pompe</hi> hurteth, and <hi>age</hi> changeth; the <hi>greater</hi> fret thee,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15628:17"/>and the <hi>leſſer</hi> flatter thee; ever in <hi>feare,</hi> never in reſt; all this but <hi>golden miſerie.</hi> When Sathan tempted our Saviour with the greateſt <hi>temptation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note> he preſumed to offer him all the <hi>kingdomes</hi> of the <hi>world,</hi> and the <hi>glory</hi> of them. It was a <hi>great offer,</hi> all the kingdomes of the <hi>world,</hi> and yet ſmall <hi>glory,</hi> that it could bee ſhewed <hi>ictu oculi,</hi> in the twinckling of an eye, as S. Luke readeth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>in an inſtant of time:</hi> the glory that is in the <hi>Celestiall kingdome, Non videt oculus,</hi> no eie hath ſeen. It was a great traunce in <hi>Peter,</hi> when at <hi>Chriſts</hi> transfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guration he cryed out, Let vs make three <hi>Tabernacles</hi> one for Thee,<note place="margin">Mat. 17.</note> one for <hi>Moſes,</hi> one for <hi>Elias: Moſes</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle was diſſolued, hee <hi>muſt haue none,</hi> hee had no commiſſion to make a new one: <hi>Elias</hi> was taken vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>heaven,</hi> he reſted on the <hi>holy hill</hi> more glorious the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to abide in a Tabernacle, hee <hi>needed none; Christ</hi> would not enioy ſo much as a hole to hide his head on <hi>earth,</hi> much leſſe a <hi>Tabernacle</hi> on a hill, hee would haue none. It had beene glorious to be preſent at the maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of that <hi>meeting,</hi> where in body, were repreſented <hi>Elias</hi> from heaven, <hi>Moſes</hi> from the graue, <hi>Peter</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from the world, nay where <hi>Pater in voce, filius in carne, ſpiritus ſanctus in nube,</hi> where the bleſſed <hi>Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> as at the <hi>Baptiſme</hi> before, ſo now againe at the <hi>Transfiguration,</hi> were all preſent, the Father in the <hi>voice,</hi> the Sonne in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> the holy ſpirit in the <hi>cloud,</hi> as the <hi>ancients</hi> haue collected. Vpon this ſhort ſhewe of the glorious preſence of <hi>Chriſt, Peter</hi> was in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie, <hi>faciamus Tabernacula,</hi> yet this <hi>felictie</hi> had bin but <hi>momentary,</hi> if <hi>made Tabernacles had ſerved,</hi> though S.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15628:17"/>
               <hi>Peter</hi> had made them; for Saint <hi>Paule</hi> telleth vs, <hi>Non manufactum Tabernaculum,</hi> it is not a Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle made with <hi>handes</hi> will ſerue, but the <hi>true Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle which the Lord hath pitcht and not man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 8.2.</note> and which <hi>David</hi> asked of in his 15. Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.1.</note> 
               <hi>Lord who ſhall dwell in thy Tabernacle, who ſhall rest vpon thy holy hil?</hi> The <hi>Monarches</hi> of the earth that ſhall enter <hi>herein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> may caſt away their <hi>crownes,</hi> as <hi>Elias</hi> left his <hi>cloake,</hi> and repent of nothing, ſaue that they <hi>came no ſooner hither.</hi> It was as it ſeemeth an <hi>honourables,</hi> and a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable</hi> ambition in the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> that there was a ſtrife among them who ſhoulde bee <hi>the greateſt in the kingdome of heaven.</hi> Mat. 18.1. Their other ambitious thoughts were not ſo law full. It was, I confeſſe a <hi>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous</hi> ſight to ſee the <hi>Saviours</hi> ſervants, (who ſhould not haue <hi>ſavoured</hi> of earthly things) diſputing who ſhould be <hi>the greatest among them,</hi> as in <hi>Marke</hi> 9.34. &amp; a much more <hi>prodigious ſpectacle</hi> to behold a <hi>contentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> among them, in an <hi>ambitious</hi> manner at the <hi>Lords ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> in the time of the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> Luk. 22.24. nay of the <hi>laſt Paſſeover</hi> that ever Chriſt did eate with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which he had <hi>deſired with ſuch a deſire</hi> to eate with them: it was much to diſpute it, more to ſtriue for it, much to queſtion in the way, <hi>contention</hi> for it at the Table, much to doe it, when their <hi>Lord</hi> heard them not as in <hi>Marke,</hi> when no <hi>danger</hi> neere their <hi>Lord:</hi> more now when their Lord heard them, and they ſaw him in <hi>ſorrow,</hi> when it was but the day before his death, &amp; bitter <hi>Paſſion,</hi> then his <hi>comfort</hi> a quarrell of his <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples;</hi> this <hi>Paſsover</hi> was truely <hi>eaten with bitter hearbes.</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:15628:18"/>Both theſe <hi>contentions</hi> were grievous in common men, more grievous in the <hi>lights</hi> and <hi>fathers,</hi> &amp; <hi>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots,</hi> and <hi>horſemen</hi> of Iſrael. But the queſtion propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in S. <hi>Mathew</hi> 18.1. may ſeeme <hi>tolerable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.1.</note> for our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> had taught <hi>them, Primum quaerite Regnum Dei,</hi> firſt ſeeke the kingdome of God, and now they deſire but to learne <hi>Quis primus in regno Dei,</hi> who ſhould be the firſt and greateſt in the kingdome of God. And in the anſwer to this ſeeming <hi>tolerable,</hi> and <hi>Commendable</hi> queſtion, Chriſt not only <hi>teacheth</hi> but taxeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the <hi>ſwelling ambition</hi> of that queſtion, and anſwereth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that vnles they were converted, &amp; would become as <hi>little children,</hi> they could not enter into the <hi>kingdom</hi> of <hi>heaven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.4.</note> He inſtanceth in <hi>a little child</hi> thus, <hi>Whoſoever therfore ſhal humble himſelfe,</hi> as this <hi>little child,</hi> the ſame <hi>is greatest in the kingdome of heaven:</hi> teaching thereby that <hi>Humility</hi> is the gate to <hi>heaven,</hi> that though the <hi>childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God</hi> muſt lead an <hi>inoffe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiue kind of life,</hi> yet they thinke <hi>meanely</hi> of themſelues, and the <hi>more holy</hi> a <hi>man</hi> is, the more hath he <hi>ſenſe</hi> of his owne <hi>corruption.</hi> Hee muſt walke with <hi>God,</hi> &amp; yet <hi>humble himſelfe</hi> vnder the <hi>mighty hand of God.</hi> No <hi>opinion</hi> in his own <hi>wiſdome,</hi> no <hi>confidence</hi> in his <hi>owne power,</hi> no <hi>hope</hi> in his owne <hi>works,</hi> he muſt deny himſelfe if he profeſſe <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And here by the <hi>conſequence</hi> of the <hi>inſtance,</hi> he reproveth his <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> that did confound the <hi>good motion,</hi> by the ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>diſpoſition</hi> of their <hi>minde,</hi> not content to bee <hi>inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritours</hi> of the kingdome of <hi>heaven,</hi> but tooke vpon them, to ſtriue for <hi>ſuperiority</hi> in that <hi>kingdome,</hi> where the meaneſt <hi>inhabitant</hi> ſhall be <hi>a king,</hi> the meaneſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15628:18"/>a <hi>Crowne,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> ſhalbe like the <hi>Angels of God.</hi> Where our <hi>New-borne Prince</hi> now is, and enioyeth a <hi>permanent</hi> triumph, moſt glorious among them, that <hi>follow the Lamb</hi> whither ſo ever he goeth, among thoſe which are redeemed, from among men, and are the <hi>firſt fruits</hi> vnto <hi>God,</hi> and to the <hi>Lamb,</hi> having there the <hi>Royalty</hi> of <hi>happyneſse,</hi> as he had here the <hi>right</hi> of <hi>inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Ambition</hi> could not <hi>tempte</hi> him, nor <hi>ſlaunder</hi> ſtaine him, that ever his <hi>thoughts</hi> did ſeeke that which was not <hi>lawful;</hi> neither in his <hi>intentions</hi> did he <hi>approue</hi> nor in his <hi>actions</hi> did appeare any ſhew of <hi>vniuſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Fas.</note> 
               <hi>Fas</hi> was <hi>the limitation of all his reſolutions.</hi> The ancient <hi>revenewes</hi> which his <hi>Royal progenitors</hi> had deſigned in his <hi>Principality</hi> and <hi>Dukedome,</hi> he regained fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vniuſt <hi>poſseſsors</hi> (for the <hi>Patrimony</hi> of <hi>Prince</hi> &amp; <hi>Prieſt</hi> hath been, &amp; is intruded vpon,) but ſuch Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>clemency</hi> herein <hi>appeared,</hi> that <hi>law</hi> having reſtored their <hi>landes</hi> and <hi>revenevves</hi> vnto his <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> his <hi>gracious bounty</hi> reſtored the <hi>poſſeſſours</hi> vpon ſmall <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations</hi> vnto that which without <hi>right</hi> they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly had <hi>detayned.</hi> Hereby giving <hi>a taſte</hi> as well of <hi>Provident</hi> managing of his <hi>state,</hi> as of his <hi>benigne</hi> regarde of any, that had any <hi>tenure</hi> vnder him, as if his lawe had beene rather <hi>Ius Praetorium,</hi> then <hi>Ius Cenſorium,</hi> and he had affected the rules of <hi>Chauncery,</hi> more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>kings bench:</hi> what <hi>Equity</hi> did yeeld him, his <hi>Clemency</hi> moderated, and <hi>law</hi> in his breaſt was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended as <hi>Virgo</hi> in heaven, as with <hi>Leo</hi> on the one ſide the power of <hi>a Prince,</hi> ſo with <hi>libra</hi> on the other ſide,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15628:19"/>
               <hi>ſcales</hi> to try the weight of <hi>right,</hi> wherein, as in the <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſcales</hi> of <hi>omnipotency,</hi> ſo in his <hi>weights,</hi> the <hi>worth</hi> of <hi>mercy,</hi> outweighed the <hi>right</hi> of <hi>Iustice.</hi> So farre was he from gathering the <hi>Treaſures</hi> of <hi>wickedneſſe,</hi> by the <hi>balance</hi> of <hi>deceit,</hi> from countenancing <hi>Lawes</hi> to bee <hi>ſnares</hi> to good mindes, or quirkes to <hi>mercenary wits,</hi> from denying the <hi>Kings meaſure</hi> to any man, or tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Iudgement</hi> into <hi>wormewood,</hi> that in many things he deſiſted from acquiring his own right: when the right hand of <hi>aequitie</hi> led him thereto: though the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then obſerved that Iuſtice is a <hi>vertue</hi> in <hi>nature,</hi> ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning with the <hi>heart</hi> of man, that there is no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>ſympathy</hi> betweene the <hi>Loadſtone</hi> &amp; <hi>Iron,</hi> then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and the <hi>heart.</hi> So that in a <hi>Prince</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, abſolute <hi>Iuſtice</hi> in its rigour, cannot ſeeme defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; that of <hi>Heraclitus</hi> being moſt true, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Prince</hi> the Image of God,<note place="margin">Heracl.</note> the <hi>Law,</hi> the worke of the <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> the end of the <hi>Law;</hi> yet ſuch a ſweet match was in the temper of the abſolute <hi>Prince,</hi> that as hee never paſſed over the <hi>Line</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> in wreſting any thing from the true owner, ſo did hee not neglect the <hi>exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe</hi> of much <hi>clemency,</hi> even vnto thoſe that vniuſtly, &amp; ſome of them vnmanerly had intruded into, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued long in the Rights of <hi>Princely</hi> demaines. As all that had occaſions to negotiate with his <hi>Highnes</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thie officers of <hi>Revenewes</hi> in the ſetling of <hi>eſtates,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but confeſſe out of a due conſideration, if any ſparke of <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>integritie</hi> be in them; as I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge much in many of them, contemning the vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15628:19"/>tongues of <hi>malignant</hi> and <hi>mad</hi> Detractors. Right was the <hi>levell,</hi> and <hi>ſquare</hi> that ruled him; <hi>kingdomes</hi> or <hi>Empires</hi> were not forcible enough, much leſſe the <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion</hi> of ſome ſmall <hi>Cantons,</hi> or <hi>Countries</hi> able to withdrawe his <hi>eye,</hi> and <hi>heart,</hi> and <hi>hand,</hi> from a iuſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, or his foot from the path of lawfull <hi>proceeding.</hi> His ſoule abhorred the ſpeech of <hi>Polynices</hi> in the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie, <hi>Imperia precio quovis conſtant benè</hi> kingdomes in his opinion were not to be bought at any rate.<note place="margin">Sen. Trag.</note> He eſteemed <hi>Power</hi> without <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> our of <hi>courſe,</hi> as a <hi>Lion</hi> broke from his <hi>cage,</hi> furious &amp; vnſatiable: vniuſt <hi>ſuits</hi> he held blots of the <hi>Courts</hi> and enimies of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> vniuſt <hi>warres</hi> abuſe of <hi>force,</hi> the <hi>vſurie</hi> of <hi>fraud;</hi> vniuſt <hi>claymes, Contentions fire,</hi> and <hi>Opinions</hi> falſhood; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt <hi>poſſeſsions</hi> as <hi>Ahabs</hi> vinyard, though the <hi>acts of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> yet the <hi>dwellings of horror. Iniustice</hi> in any caſe, was not only <hi>distaſted</hi> but <hi>deteſted</hi> by him, hee yeelded no <hi>countenance,</hi> no <hi>encouragement</hi> to ſuch acquiſitions. <hi>Rapine</hi> durſt never fly for ſhelter vnder his ſhadow, it feared, nay it fled his <hi>countenance;</hi> neither his <hi>practiſe,</hi> nor <hi>protection</hi> yeelded favour to that horrid <hi>Pyoner</hi> &amp; <hi>Monſter</hi> of the <hi>Palace, Iniuſtice: Fas eſt,</hi> was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> calleth it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as S. <hi>Iames</hi> tearmeth it, an vnwritten, yet a <hi>Royall</hi> law to him. The Portion of the <hi>Levite</hi> hee eſteemed ſacred, <hi>ſacriledge</hi> he accounted as <hi>neighbour to blaſphemie;</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> was as happy by him, as he by it <hi>holy:</hi> he wiſht the <hi>Arke</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> their dignitie and dues; not the meaneſt of that tribe, but had from him vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, more reſpect then from the moſt of that time; and for their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15628:20"/>
               <hi>maintenance,</hi> by his <hi>Religious Arithmetique,</hi> hee inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded rather <hi>addition</hi> to it then <hi>ſubſtraction</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever to the contrary was thought by ſome hot ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, <hi>Heroſtratus heires,</hi> who thinke to get honour by ſetting <hi>fire</hi> on the Temple: No place complained of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Iniuſtice</hi> in him, much leſſe <hi>Gods houſe,</hi> or the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance thereof. The Temple was his high way to <hi>heaven,</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> his guid, <hi>felicitie</hi> the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie he expected, and yet <hi>violence</hi> the meanes by which he ſought it. Was violence the meanes? Sacred <hi>Prince!</hi> he was another <hi>Moſes,</hi> the meekeſt that ever his name ſtiled great, <hi>Anger</hi> was a <hi>stranger,</hi> and <hi>Paſſion</hi> an <hi>exile</hi> with him, his <hi>pulſes</hi> equall, ſpeeches temperat, his <hi>countenance</hi> as the ſunne in it ſelfe, alwaies faire, his <hi>entendments</hi> iuſt, and <hi>actions</hi> iuditious. Where then had violence either dwelling or lodging in him? <hi>Nec irritabilis nec implacabilis;</hi> hee was not eaſily angred, yet eaſily pleaſed, a ſtorme could not ſmite him, nor the violence, which <hi>ſhipwrackt</hi> others, ſhake him. <hi>Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum non patitur,</hi> this celeſtiall creature was not ſubiect to the paſſiue motions of <hi>diſtempers:</hi> the change of the <hi>moone</hi> had not power, nor the violence of <hi>Planets</hi> predominancy in his <hi>Nativitie.</hi> In all his <hi>ſayling,</hi> hee was in a <hi>calme,</hi> hee had learnt the leſſon which was taught to <hi>Traian, Nec minus ſe hominem eſse quàm homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus praeeſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pliny.</note> His practiſe was as much in the <hi>Politikes</hi> to obey, as in his <hi>Oeconomicks</hi> to rule: and how then was violence the meanes of his acquiſition? I ſay again <hi>Violence</hi> was the meanes to obtaine his <hi>felicitie,</hi> even that holy ſanctified <hi>violence,</hi> which our Saviour ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15628:20"/>vnto, Mat. 11.22.<note place="margin">Mat. 11.12.</note> The kingdome of heaven muſt ſuffer violence, and the violent take it by force. The Saints of God ſhall drinke of the <hi>Flood</hi> of <hi>life,</hi> Pſ. 36.9. The holy ſpirit deſcended in a <hi>fire,</hi> Acts 2. And what more violent then a <hi>flood,</hi> or <hi>fire?</hi> In what is ſo much <hi>earnestneſſe</hi> ſhewed, as in a <hi>race,</hi> or a <hi>Combat?</hi> yet theſe be the <hi>tearmes</hi> of Scripture, to incite to a more vrgent violent pace in our paſſage towardes heaven. Which <hi>Courſe,</hi> as this Peereleſſe <hi>Creature</hi> knew, ſo did he with his beſt affections bend towards it, <hi>Spirituall pride,</hi> and <hi>carnall ſecuritie</hi> were rockes on either hand him, which hee <hi>avoided,</hi> a continuall <hi>remembrance</hi> of his <hi>Creator,</hi> the Lord that <hi>directed</hi> him, and as if his <hi>veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel</hi> had beene more <hi>ſpeedy</hi> then <hi>ordinary,</hi> hee happily paſſed through the <hi>waues</hi> of this troubleſome <hi>world,</hi> and <hi>ankor</hi> in the <hi>haven</hi> of <hi>heaven,</hi> vnto which hee had the heigth of <hi>inheritance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 Learne from this <hi>Holy patterne,</hi> all yee that torture <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and extend the limits of <hi>right</hi> to your own ends, vſing the Law, as a Law of libertie, <hi>bla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ching</hi> of <hi>bad, darkning</hi> of <hi>good</hi> courſes, changing the face &amp; ſpeech of <hi>Iustice,</hi> making her <hi>pronounce</hi> as the heathen <hi>Oracles,</hi> often <hi>ambiguitie,</hi> if not <hi>falſities.</hi> Behold a <hi>Prince,</hi> whoſe <hi>power</hi> might haue betrayed his <hi>will,</hi> and his <hi>will</hi> corrupted the <hi>Law,</hi> but hee <hi>walketh vpright be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his maker, violence</hi> or <hi>crueltie</hi> had no place in his <hi>habitations,</hi> all his <hi>intentions</hi> were weighed, with how <hi>lawfull,</hi> not how <hi>gainefull</hi> they were: the kingdome of <hi>heaven</hi> to which he had right by <hi>adoption</hi> is his ayme, is his deſire; to ſeeke other <hi>things</hi> if this were any <hi>hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:15628:21"/>to this <hi>atchieument</hi> he forbore: hereby teaching the <hi>vnrighteous Ahabs</hi> of this time, who ſeeke for all things elſe but <hi>heaven,</hi> by all means elſe but <hi>right,</hi> how great their <hi>offence</hi> is, who in the placing of their <hi>offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi> be like <hi>Nero,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eraſ. Apoth.</note> whoſe ſpeech was to his ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, <hi>ſcitis quibus mihi opus. &amp; hoc agamus ne quis quid habeat,</hi> as if his treaſures ſhould haue beene the <hi>Ocean</hi> into which the rivers of privat mens <hi>ſtates</hi> ſhould haue emptied themſelues: <hi>Vox praedone, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> principe dignior,</hi> a ſpeech fitter for a <hi>Pyrat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lang loc. Com.</note> then a <hi>Prince,</hi> as one cenſureth him. Where if ſuch would bee <hi>content,</hi> to prey onely on the <hi>great ones,</hi> the fault were leſſe, as <hi>Tibullus</hi> telleth the great <hi>theeues</hi> of his time,</p>
            <q>At vos exiguo peeori fureſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> lupí<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>
               <note place="margin">Tibull.</note>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Farcite: de magno praeda petenda grege.</hi> It cauſed <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> anger to be greatly <hi>kindled</hi> againſt the rich man in <hi>Nathans</hi> parable, who tooke away from <hi>the poore man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.</note> the one, and <hi>onely little ewe Lambe, which he had bought and nouriſhed vp;</hi> and <hi>David</hi> ſentenceth it thus, <hi>As the Lord liueth, the man that hath done this thing ſhall ſurely die,</hi> and he ſhall <hi>reſtore</hi> the <hi>Lambe</hi> fourefold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did this <hi>thing,</hi> and becauſe he had <hi>no pity,</hi> 2. Sam. 12.6. And not to heape <hi>teſtimonies,</hi> that one of <hi>Caſſiodore</hi> is enough,<note place="margin">Caſſ. lib <hi>5.</hi> Ep.</note> 
               <hi>Vltra omnes crudelitates eſt divite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> velle fieri ex exiguitate mendici. Amentur honesta lucra, horreantur damnoſa compendia. Pudeat ab illus tollere qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus inhemur offerre.</hi> It is <hi>cruelty</hi> in the <hi>abſtract</hi> that anie man ſhould <hi>grow</hi> rich by excorting from the poore; <hi>honest</hi> gaine is <hi>lawfull,</hi> damned <hi>rapine</hi> hatefull: the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame</hi> of ſhame is to <hi>take</hi> from them, to whom wee
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15628:21"/>are <hi>commanded</hi> to giue. God heareth their cries, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth their ſighes, putteth vp their <hi>teares;</hi> their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints as <hi>darts</hi> pearce heaven. The obſervation of <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> is worthy, that of all the bleſſings of our <hi>Sauiour</hi> in the <hi>Mount,</hi> the bleſſing of <hi>inheritance</hi> is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given to the <hi>meeke,</hi> Mat. 5.5. Bleſſed are <hi>the meek, for they ſhall inherite the earth.</hi> Which is mainely contrary to the courſe of <hi>the world?</hi> for if meekeneſſe were the beſt fortreſſe for <hi>poſseſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> how ſo one would the <hi>ſnares</hi> and <hi>ſubtilties</hi> of <hi>Law-wreſting vnderminers,</hi> prevaile! <hi>wherefore</hi> the violent <hi>Nebuchadnezars</hi> of the <hi>world,</hi> by <hi>vſurpation</hi> rather then by <hi>poſſeſſion,</hi> retaine their ſeats, &amp; may be ſaid rather to <hi>inhabit</hi> then <hi>inherite</hi> the land. But vnto the <hi>Godly</hi> ſaith God; <hi>What man is he that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Lorde? him ſhall hee teach in the way that he ſhall chooſe,</hi> his <hi>ſoule</hi> ſhall dwel at eaſe, and his <hi>ſeed</hi> ſhal inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite the land, Pſal. 24.12. Not only the <hi>meeke</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues but <hi>their ſeed,</hi> ſhal not only <hi>poſſeſſe</hi> but <hi>inherit,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the earth but the <hi>land</hi> of the <hi>living;</hi> when as the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt <hi>Intruders</hi> ſhall make but the <hi>ſpiders</hi> neſt, or build their houſes, as vpon the <hi>ſands,</hi> a <hi>winde</hi> will come to caſt downe their <hi>Palaces,</hi> &amp; to root them out of their <hi>poſſeſsions,</hi> &amp; to rot their <hi>memoriall</hi> from of the earth. When as, they that by <hi>right</hi> &amp; <hi>righteous</hi> dealing haue enioyed the bleſſing of <hi>inheritance,</hi> ſhall ſhine by their <hi>good works</hi> while they <hi>liue,</hi> and by their <hi>good name</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are dead; as now this Gratious <hi>Glorious Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant</hi> Saint doth, whoſe name ſhall bee <hi>had in everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting remembrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It a in ſingulis virtutibus eminebat,</hi> He was ſo <hi>emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:15628:22"/>in every vertue, to vſe <hi>S. Hieroms</hi> words, that with out much <hi>amplification</hi> the <hi>Apophthegmes</hi> of his own life, will furniſh a <hi>large</hi> diſcourſe. He was never beaten down with his <hi>owne paſſions,</hi> but did conquer his own <hi>conquerours;</hi> his <hi>anger</hi> ſerved only to <hi>enflame his zeale,</hi> height of <hi>ſpirit,</hi> to <hi>deſpiſe the world, Feare,</hi> only to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine <hi>from ſin, ioy</hi> to <hi>praiſe God, ſadneſſe</hi> to <hi>repent, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred,</hi> to <hi>purſue vice loue,</hi> to <hi>enſue vertue;</hi> ſo his paſſions, being ſubdued as <hi>Rebels,</hi> were ſingular helps in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of <hi>vertue.</hi> And for <hi>himſelfe,</hi> and his worthy fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, the words of <hi>Hierome of Nepotia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> will fitly ſerue the cloſe of this diſcourſe <hi>Domus eius, &amp; converſatio, magistra erat publicae diſciplinae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hier.</note> his owne Princely <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,</hi> &amp; the courſe of his <hi>houſe</hi> was a <hi>miſtreſſe</hi> (or rather a <hi>mirrour</hi>) <hi>of publike diſcipline,</hi> the modell of a wel-managed <hi>ſtate. Mars</hi> &amp; <hi>Minerva</hi> dwelt in his <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace,</hi> which in it ſelfe was a ſecond <hi>Paradiſe. Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> was of his <hi>privy chamber,</hi> and <hi>vertue</hi> a great officer in his <hi>houſe, knowledge</hi> was a <hi>companion</hi> with him, good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations had breeding here, and good men <hi>prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and his <hi>Countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce did change the face of the times.</hi> But as <hi>Ceſtius</hi> in <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpake of <hi>Altius Flavius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Senec. Lib. <hi>2.</hi> Cont. con. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turè magnum ingentum non eſſe vitabo,</hi> it proved to bee a <hi>fatall Truth</hi> in him, that ſo <hi>great a ſpirit,</hi> ſo <hi>ſoone</hi> to appeare, was a <hi>prodigious</hi> ſigne of the loſſe, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued by the end of his life, ſuch an <hi>Epiphany</hi> was the ſpeedy forerunner of <hi>his mortality.</hi> No <hi>preuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> could ſtay the <hi>wheele</hi> running at the <hi>Cesterne of his life,</hi> his daies were <hi>numbred,</hi> the <hi>ſtealing ſteps</hi> and inſenſible <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees</hi> of <hi>death</hi> did approach even <hi>like the ſunne,</hi> which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15628:22"/>
               <hi>maintaineth a very ſwift motion,</hi> yet doth not the <hi>eie</hi> perceiue it to <hi>moue. Death</hi> the Tyraunt, exerciſed his <hi>rage,</hi> with the <hi>greateſt cruelty vpon this Princely ſubiect,</hi> and <hi>ſuddenly cropt of,</hi> this faireſt of <hi>Natures flowers</hi> and overthrew him in the Principall ſtrength, and beauty of his age: at which <hi>blow, the world ſtaggred, &amp; being old and nought it feared the date of its owne diſſolution.</hi> All naturall things, muſt encreaſe and decline, the <hi>ſunne</hi> ſhal end the courſe &amp; conſume, heaven ſhall be wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vp as a <hi>ſcrowle,</hi> and the ſtarres ſhall <hi>fall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal.</note> 
               <hi>Death doth reſtraine the ſpirit of Princes and is wonderfull among the ſonnes of the earth.</hi> It was the laſt leſſon that ever this <hi>excellent Prince</hi> was publikely taught, that though co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dare not be acquainted with kings, yet death is more commonly boiſtrous and more violent with kings, then other men, <hi>Of all the kings of Iudah, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboam downe to Zedekiah, there were in number twenty, and ſix of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is almoſt a third part ſlaine; of the kings of Iſrael from Ieroboam to Oſhea, there were alſo in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber twenty, and ten of them a iuſt halfe ſlaine, yea looke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our owne ſtories and our Engliſh Chronicles are all blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from the Conquest downward of three &amp; twenty decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, eight which is more then a third part ſlaine:</hi> wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the<note n="*" place="margin">M. <hi>Wilkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> who prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at S. Iames that day his Highneſſe ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> Reverend Preacher co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded, it were a moſt <hi>fearefull</hi> thing amongſt the common ſort of men, if one, in every three were ſubiect to ſuch violent death. But <hi>Death</hi> durſt not come with ſuch <hi>violence,</hi> nor ſo rudely intrude into this Princely <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> it came in by ſtealth, yet being <hi>entred,</hi> it ſeverely did exact <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> it expugned all <hi>deſences</hi> againſt it, &amp; vndermining
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15628:23"/>all <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> was not content with bloud, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands <hi>life:</hi> when <hi>Natures</hi> frame ſeemed firme, and a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance</hi> appeared in this <hi>Divine Prince,</hi> Death led him into the vnavoidable paſſage of the fartheſt &amp; faireſt path of nature, &amp; kept him 13. daies in this <hi>Labyrinth.</hi> In which time, dayly changing, daily <hi>dying,</hi> HE, though entangled in the ſnares of diſeaſe, yet avoided the ſnakes of diſtruſt or diſtemper, &amp; with a noble <hi>Courage</hi> like the ſunne, did ſhew greateſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, in this loweſt <hi>ſtate,</hi> and with a braue yet bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed behaviour in contempt <hi>of death,</hi> gaue a <hi>grace</hi> to the greateſt extremities the <hi>Tyraunt</hi> could deviſe: for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Tragické Monſter, ſtopt his <hi>breath cloſed</hi> his <hi>eies</hi> &amp; drewe the <hi>curtaines,</hi> the Princely <hi>ſoule</hi> tooke <hi>wing</hi> and with troupes of <hi>Angels</hi> fled to heaven.</p>
            <p>It is not without warrant,<note place="margin">O Death!</note> that God <hi>diſclaimeth</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny intereſt in thee, thou <hi>Infernall</hi> yet <hi>Imperiall</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander: he hath <hi>pronounced</hi> by the mouth of the <hi>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he never made thee, but that thou hadſt thine en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try into the world by the very malice and ſubtiltie of the Divell.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wiſd 1.13.2.24.</note> Haſt thou hurried about the <hi>world,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed the <hi>whole earth</hi> to and fro? and haſt thou conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered <hi>Great Henry,</hi> who was perfect and vpright, one that <hi>feared God, and eſchewed evill,</hi> and haſt thou privily ſhot at him that was true of heart? Curſed bee thy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, for it was fierce, and thy <hi>wrath</hi> it was <hi>cruell!</hi> Didſt thou miſtake <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> for <hi>Ahab?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 22.32</note> this <hi>holy</hi> Prince, for ſome <hi>Idolatrous Pagan?</hi> or was thy aime onely at this <hi>beautie</hi> of the <hi>world?</hi> Why hadſt thou not <hi>gorged</hi> thy hollow helliſh appetite, with ſome blaſphemous
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15628:23"/>
               <hi>Rabſhaked,</hi> or curſed <hi>Sanballat,</hi> with ſome aſpiring <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> or Church-robbing <hi>Nebuchadnezzar?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">
               <note place="margin">Ioſeph lib. <hi>1.</hi> Antiq. cap. <hi>5.</hi> Hoſp. de Grig. fiſt pag <hi>48.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemb.</note>12 <hi>November</hi> was the <hi>diſmall</hi> time death fitted for this <hi>Tragedy,</hi> a time noted by the Orator <hi>dyſaſtrous.</hi> It would rather fill a <hi>Library,</hi> then a <hi>volume</hi> to deſcend to <hi>particulars.</hi> It was the Month of the <hi>Flood,</hi> as <hi>Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> among the ancient, &amp; <hi>Hoſpinian</hi> among the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne doe <hi>affirme:</hi> and if ever a ſecond <hi>Cataclyſme</hi> fell vpon the <hi>earth,</hi> the <hi>Teares</hi> ſhed in the <hi>ſorrow</hi> of this <hi>loſſe,</hi> may <hi>deſerue a Chronicle;</hi> many expectations were ſunke, and ſome <hi>Gallants</hi> went to <hi>heave thy water, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row killed them.</hi> What <hi>hopes</hi> were ſhipwrackt in this ſtorme, and what a generall <hi>deluge,</hi> over ſtreamed all <hi>honest hearts,</hi> will never be <hi>forgotten,</hi> while that blacke day, the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>November</hi> ſhall appeare in our <hi>Kalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Quintus intendit, Sextus intulit.</hi> The 5. day was by the Sonnes of <hi>Beliall</hi> a day dedicated to our <hi>deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> a day by <hi>Heſiod,</hi> and <hi>Virgil,</hi> and all the <hi>heathens,</hi> as <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpinian</hi> collecteth, moſt <hi>ominous:</hi> but the Lord was more <hi>carefull</hi> in the <hi>prevention,</hi> then wee <hi>thankfull</hi> for <hi>preſervation</hi> herein; therefore what was but <hi>threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> on the <hi>fift day</hi> was <hi>ſhowred</hi> downe the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day, at <hi>which time the ſtorme fell vpon vs.</hi> It was a <hi>ſtrange</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digie, that on the fift day at <hi>night,</hi> about the houre of 8. a <hi>Rainebow</hi> appeared, ſeeming as it were by the <hi>ſight</hi> and <hi>Iudgement</hi> of ſome, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe the <hi>houſe of S. Iames.</hi> I referre the <hi>Learned</hi> to thoſe that haue written of <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies:</hi> for my own part I haue learned that leſſon, <hi>In pluribus Domini operibus non eſſe curioſum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 3.22.</note> not to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>curious</hi> and <hi>inquiſitiue</hi> in many workes of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15628:24"/>Lactantius</hi> much inveigheth againſt thoſe,<note place="margin">De falſ. ſap. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> whoſe chiefe delight was, <hi>Inconceſſa / crutari,</hi> to ſearch for vnlawfull things; and I knowe that <hi>Iacob</hi> ſtriving with an <hi>Angell,</hi> got the ſhrinking of a <hi>ſinew:</hi> yet that the covena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the <hi>flood,</hi> ſould ſo dyſaſtrouſly appeare in the month of the <hi>flood,</hi> in the night beyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the rules of <hi>Nature,</hi> and courſe of <hi>cuſtome,</hi> did certainely por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſomewhat. Indeed after the <hi>flood</hi> God hung vp his <hi>bowe</hi> in the <hi>Clowd,</hi> in token of <hi>reconciliation vnto men,</hi> and the <hi>bend</hi> and arch of the <hi>bowe</hi> is turned from vs,<note place="margin">Lib. de operibus creat. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Zanchius</hi> obſerveth. But he hung vp his <hi>bow,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ambroſe, Arcus habet vulneris indicium, non vulneris effectum,</hi> the bowe maketh a ſhewe of <hi>hurting,</hi> but it doth not <hi>hurt,</hi> it is the arrow that <hi>woundeth.</hi> But now God ſeemeth for our <hi>ſinnes,</hi> to haue taken downe his <hi>bow</hi> againe, it was an arrow he ſhot with the <hi>fervency</hi> of his <hi>furie,</hi> the Court was <hi>wounded,</hi> the <hi>Commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>wealth;</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> the whole <hi>Proteſtant</hi> world receaved a wound, in the death of Gods <hi>deareling,</hi> the <hi>Renowned Prince</hi> now in <hi>heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13 Let all the world ſtand in awe of their pow erfull commander, that ſhooteth his arrowes of deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation among the <hi>Children</hi> of men. All the trees of the <hi>Foreſt</hi> muſt know, that the Lord hath brought down the <hi>high tree,</hi> hath exalted the <hi>lowe tree,</hi> hath dried vp the <hi>greene tree,</hi> and hath made the <hi>dry tree</hi> to flouriſh as he <hi>threatneth</hi> Ezek. 17.24. and that all the ſonnes of men are vnder one <hi>common conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Our <hi>liues</hi> are <hi>ſhort</hi> in all things except <hi>miſeries</hi> and <hi>troubles,</hi> our continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is only certaine in vncertaintie. God hath reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15628:24"/>our times, vnknowne, becauſe wee ſhould bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ready.</p>
            <q>Quò propior quiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> eſt, ſervit<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> fideliùsaegro</q>
            <p>
               <hi>In partem laethi citiùs venit.</hi> By how much the neerer men come about dying <hi>perſons,</hi> by ſo much the ſooner ſhould they conſider their owne deaths. Wherefore <hi>Noble</hi> and <hi>worthy Gentlemen,</hi> who were ſad <hi>ſpectators</hi> of the bleſſed paſſage of his <hi>Princely</hi> ſoul, ſequeſter all humane wiſdome and policy, all <hi>Court</hi> vanitie or glory, looke vpon the <hi>Glaſse</hi> of mortalitie; the more yee are <hi>intangled</hi> either in the <hi>delights</hi> or <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires</hi> of this life, the more grievous death will bee to you. It will be vnſeaſonable, when the <hi>paines</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities</hi> of the <hi>ſoules</hi> departing from two friends of ſo long <hi>familiarity,</hi> the <hi>body</hi> and the <hi>world,</hi> ſhal draw your powers from true repentance. Seeke therefore the Lord while he may bee found, blowe the <hi>dying fire</hi> of your <hi>devotion.</hi> Looke backe, and eſteeme the whole race which yee haue runne, as a <hi>ſhort ſteppe,</hi> looke fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and behold the infinit ſpace of <hi>eternitie,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by grace yee may continue: here yee haue no abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding city, your ſervice is no inheritance. Lift there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your mindes to <hi>heaven,</hi> and diſcover the <hi>moſt bright</hi> and beautifull <hi>glory; your life is your candle, wast it not in idle play, it was allowed you only to light you to ed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, whoſoever of you beholdeth the preſent <hi>Princely family,</hi> and ſaw it in her firſt <hi>glory;</hi> doubt not but God will make good his <hi>word</hi> to this houſe, which he promiſed in <hi>Haggci, The glory of this later houſe ſhall be</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:15628:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>greater then the former,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hag. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>ſaith the Lord of hoſts.</hi> Lord make this promiſe good. Bleſſe our moſt hopefull <hi>Charlemaine</hi> with all thy choiſe <hi>graces. Let the enimie haue none advantage of him, nor the wieked approach to hurt him: but for ever let thy mercies compaſſe him, giue vnto him the doubled ſpirit of his now bleſſed and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall brother; indue him with the hand of Gedeon, the heart of David, and the head of Solomon. Grant him in health and wealth long to liue, that at the length hee may attaine everlaſting ioy and felicitie through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15628:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
